<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ancient and modern delusions, discoursed of in three sermons upon 2 Thes. 2.11 concerning some errors now prevailing in the Church of Rome / by Edward Pelling ...</title>
            <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53945</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1071</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R13403</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12033649</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12033649</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52826</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53945)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52826)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 573:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ancient and modern delusions, discoursed of in three sermons upon 2 Thes. 2.11 concerning some errors now prevailing in the Church of Rome / by Edward Pelling ...</title>
                  <author>Pelling, Edward, d. 1718.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 58, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B.G. for Jonathan Edwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement: p. [1]-[2] at end.</note>
                  <note>Includes bibliographical references.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Thessalonians, 2nd, II, 11 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:52826:1"/>
            <p>IMPRIMATUR.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>March</hi> 28. 1679.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Guil. Sill. R. P. D. Henr. Epiſc. Lond. à Sac. Dom.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52826:1"/>
            <p>ANCIENT and MODERN DELUSIONS, Diſcourſed of in Three Sermons Upon 2 THES. 2. 11.</p>
            <p>Concerning ſome ERRORS now prevailing in the CHURCH OF ROME.</p>
            <p>By <hi>EDWARD PELLING,</hi> Rector of St. <hi>Martins Ludgate, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Etiamſi ingeritur oculis Veritas, amat &amp; tuetur errorem: coargui non vult; &amp; in malè caeptis honeſtior illi pertinacia videtur, quàm Penitentia.</hi> 
               <bibl>Sen. de ira, lib. 1. c. 16.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>B. G.</hi> for <hi>Jonathan Edwin</hi> at the three Roſes in <hi>Ludgate-ſtreet,</hi> 1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:52826:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52826:2"/>
            <head>ANCIENT and MODERN DELUSIONS, Diſcourſed of in three SERMONS Upon 2 THES. 2. 11.</head>
            <head>SERM. I.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2. THES. 2. 11.</bibl>
               <q>And for this cauſe God ſhall ſend them ſtrong Delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, that they ſhould believe a Lye.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Think, there is not in all the New Teſtament, a Chapter which has been more quoted by Proteſtants than <hi>this:</hi> And he, that ſhall read the former part thereof, may be apt to conceive, that S. <hi>Paul,</hi> by a <hi>Prophetick Spirit,</hi> pointeth here to the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Biſhops of Rome.</hi> And I confeſs, many Learned Divines have thought ſo, becauſe there are in this Chapter, ſo many notable Characters which do become and fit that Faction ſo well; that though St. <hi>Paul</hi> did not point to them <hi>directly,</hi> a man might ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52826:3"/>
and plauſibly miſtake in thinking that he did. For, firſt, he tells us of a falling away (from the Faith) that was to come, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. and it is notorious, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath departed, though not from the <hi>whole Creed,</hi> yet from many <hi>Fundamental, and uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally received</hi> Doctrines of Chriſtianity. In the ſame breath, he ſpeaks of a <hi>man of ſin, that was to be revealed, the Son of Perdition;</hi> which the beſt Interpreters do underſtand not of a <hi>ſingle Perſon,</hi> but of a <hi>whole Sect;</hi> as when we ſay, the Jeſuit is a Traitor, we mean the <hi>wholer Order and Society.</hi> Moreover, the Apoſtle tells us, that this man of Sin <hi>oppoſeth and exalteth himſelf above all, that is called God, or that is worſhipped; ſo that he as God ſitteth in the Temple</hi> (or Church) <hi>of God, ſhewing himſelf that he is God.</hi> He ſpeaketh of <hi>a My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Iniquity that began to work then, whoſe coming was after the working of Satan, with all Power, and Signs, and lying Wonders.</hi> All which deſcriptions, whoſoever ſhall conſider, and compare them with the Novel Doctrines, the intollerable Uſurpations, the monſtrous Practices, and the pretended Miracles of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> may be apt to think (as ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Doctors, both before, and ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, have thought) that the Pope and his flatterers are here marked out unto us. Eſpecially, if he ſhall conſider withal, how the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. That the coming of this man of Sin would be <hi>with all deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrighteouſneſs;</hi> meaning, with all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52826:3"/>
cunning Arts of wheadling people into ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, which <hi>Cornelius a Lapide</hi> the Jeſuit, reckons to be ſix, and all of them to be uſed <note place="margin">Com. in Loc.</note> by Anti-chriſt to draw men into Errour and Deſtruction. 1. By courteous and obliging Inſinuations. 2. By ſpecious pretences of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Sanctity. 3. By their Wiſdome and Eloquence, and ſkilfulneſs in all Arts and Learning. 4. By promiſing, and bribing them with money, the more readily to bring hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry perſons to their Lure. 5. By threatning ſuch as are Refractory with Death and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, and by inflicting on them the terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Torments of an Inquiſition. 6. By work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch Prodigies and Wonders before the Eyes of the World, as ignorant and credu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous People will be ready to admire and believe, and to take for true Miracles. Now I am much deceiv'd, if this Jeſuit did not take his Meaſures by his own Brethren; ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly do theſe Arts and Methods agree with the Tricks and Manners of that ſort of Cattel, that when I read his Comment upon the Place, I fancied my ſelf to be reading the plain and perfect Character of <hi>Ignatius</hi>'s Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples.</p>
            <p>Yet, the great <hi>Hugo Grotius,</hi> and many <note place="margin">Lib. de Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſto.</note> Moderate and Judicious men beſides, do not underſtand St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to relate here <hi>immediately</hi> to the Romaniſts, though others have otherwiſe opined, whoſe zeal might have tranſported them beyond themſelves; ſuch weak Creatures we are naturally, that our Paſſions are apt to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52826:4"/>
ingage in the moſt weighty Diſputes, juſt as hot pated men are ready to <hi>thruſt</hi> into, and <hi>buſtle</hi> in the graveſt Councils. Very proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it is, that the Apoſtle in this Chapter (as in ſeveral other places) pointeth to a wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Crew of Apoſtates, that prevailed in <hi>thoſe firſt Times</hi> of Chriſtianity, as <hi>Simon Magus</hi> and his followers, who though they were divided into ſeveral Sects and Factions (the <hi>Nicolaitanes,</hi> the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> the <hi>Carpocratians,</hi> the <hi>Eucratitae,</hi> the <hi>Marcionites,</hi> and the reſt) ſome of our late Divines do comprehend (all of them) under the general name of <hi>Gnoſticks.</hi> I will not contend about this matter, being little to my purpoſe: This is certain, that whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver deceivers are intended in this place of Scripture, it was a juſt Judgement of God, upon vile and wicked men, that <hi>they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed</hi> their Ends: They gained upon ſuch or ſuch onely, as ran wilfully to their own deſtruction; ſuch as lived unrighteouſly, and loved not the Truth, but diſhonoured it and the God of it, by their fooliſh, ſenſual and lewd Courſes, <hi>for this cauſe it was, that God ſent them ſtrong Deluſion, that they ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a Lye.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that my buſineſs is to handle this Text, with reference unto thoſe chiefly, who either <hi>are</hi> already, or are <hi>likely</hi> to be Deluded; if it be poſſible, to <hi>redeem</hi> the one, and to <hi>keep</hi> the other ſort out of that ſnare, which the Devil ſpreadeth for unwary wretches, by as many Wiles and Inſtruments in theſe days of ours,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52826:4"/>
as ever he did in the dayes of the Apoſtle, or after. And in the proſecution of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I ſhall undertake to ſhew you theſe two things, by occaſion of the words, which I have now read unto you.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How it cometh to paſs, that many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are led away by ſtrong Deluſions, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that which is a manifeſt and notorious Lye.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That notwithſtanding the great eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which have been given on the behalf of Truth, yet multitudes of ſilly People are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fond of Deluſions, and Lyes ſtill; ſtrong Deluſions, groſs and palpable Lies, which are taught them by thoſe, who are, <hi>if not the ſame,</hi> yet as <hi>like</hi> unto the deceivers, whom St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of here, as one Impoſtor can be like another; and in the proceſs of this diſcourſe, I ſhall ſhew you, in particular, what ſome of thoſe Deluſions and Lies are, and how they reſemble thoſe which were broach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the beginning.</p>
            <p n="1">1. How it cometh to paſs, that many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are led away by ſtrong Deluſions, and believe that which is a manifeſt and notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lie. Certainly the Hiſtory of mankind is a very great wonder, that ſince Truth is ſo lovely and taking, ſince men are generally ſo ſolicitous and inquiſitive after it, ſince our faculties are ſo excellently framed to find it out, and are naturally ſhie of receiving any notions, which have not the <hi>ſpecies and colour</hi> of Truth; ſince men profeſs a willingneſs to buy
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52826:5"/>
it almoſt at any rate; and to value the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of it above the World, and even to ſacrifice their Lives for Truth ſake; it ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth ſtrange, that there ſhould be any ſuch <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomalous</hi> Creatures and <hi>Monſters</hi> among the Sons of men; as will care ſo little for it as to exchange it for a Lye, and not onely to plead and diſpute, but moreover to ſuffer, and become Martyrs for a Falſhood. <hi>O foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Galatians, who have betwitched you, that you ſhould not obey the Truth?</hi> Gal. 3. 1. 'Tis ſuch a <hi>ſenſeleſs</hi> thing to be in Love with Error, that none but meer <hi>Fools and Sots,</hi> and ſuch Fools as are <hi>bewitched</hi> too, can be thought capable of ſuffering themſelves willingly to be abuſed with wrong apprehenſions, eſpecially in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion. But he was not much out that divided the whole World into Cheaters and Cheatees: There are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Some that <hi>Deceive,</hi> and others that are <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived,</hi> 2 Tim. 3. 13. It has been ſo in all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and yet all Ages have admired at it: and 'tis that which we ſtand amazed at in theſe days, to ſee not only mean and ſilly People, that are but as Muſhromes of the Earth, but even Perſons of Honourable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, of Parts, and Learning, and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous minds, to be both the <hi>Diſciples</hi> and <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons</hi> of a Religion, which, of all the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions that ever were ſet up in the World, is not only the moſt <hi>Bloody,</hi> but the moſt <hi>Ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous.</hi> But the Reaſons which may be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of it, are theſe chiefly.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:52826:5"/>
1 Education, whereby men ſuck in miſtakes with their firſt milk, and have falſe Principles entailed upon them as part of their Inheritance. And queſtionleſs, great is the power of Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, it being ſo difficult a matter to raze thoſe principles out of mens minds which cleave to 'em from their <hi>Infancy,</hi> and grow up with 'em from their <hi>Cradle:</hi> eſpecially, if either the <hi>Tutor</hi> be not <hi>Faithful,</hi> or the <hi>Scholer</hi> be not <hi>Inquiſitive,</hi> or <hi>Means</hi> be not <hi>afforded</hi> for the enlightning of the underſtanding; as it is, we know, in many places beyond the Seas, where Prieſts are either <hi>ignorant</hi> or <hi>diſhoneſt,</hi> and the Layety are nurſed up in blindneſs, tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Guides for ſo many infallible Oracles, who deprive 'em of the Bible, and other uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Books, and breed 'em up, as you would breed up <hi>Pyes</hi> and <hi>Parrots,</hi> to ſay any thing, which they do not underſtand. No wonder if theſe miſerable Souls believe a thouſand things for <hi>Truths,</hi> which we, who have the means of Knowledge, plainly find to be no other than <hi>Impoſtures:</hi> and we doubt not, but God, who is rich in mercy, will Pardon the <hi>invincible Ignorance</hi> of theſe deluded wretches, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of them <hi>according to what they have, and not according to what they have not.</hi> But God be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, this is not the caſe of thoſe Romaniſts who live <hi>amongſt us.</hi> They cannot pretend, that they <hi>are not,</hi> or <hi>may not</hi> be better inſtructed, ſuch of them eſpecially, as have <hi>deſerted our Communion:</hi> 'tis not through Ignorance that <hi>They</hi> are deluded: but very probably it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52826:6"/>
that they are brought to believe a lye.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By the <hi>Love</hi> they bear to ſome <hi>baſe and ſiniſter ends.</hi> For certainly nothing doth more corrupt and abuſe Mens underſtanding, than their <hi>Affections.</hi> Either the <hi>Hatred</hi> of a party, or the <hi>Hope</hi> of Promotion, or the <hi>Fear</hi> of great mens frowns, or the <hi>Love</hi> of Riches, when they <hi>run greedily after the Errour of Balaam for reward;</hi> but above all, a <hi>deſire</hi> of gratifying their <hi>Senſual Luſts and Appetites,</hi> carrieth a mighty hand over their Reaſon, to make it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Falſehood for Truth, and to believe not that which is <hi>Righteſt,</hi> but that which is moſt <hi>popular, moſt pleaſant, and moſt advantageous.</hi> Reaſon is either the beſt or the worſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellour. When it ſits in the Throne, command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the lower faculties of the Soul, it gives True judgement and faithful directions. But when it hearkeneth to the Oratory of Intereſt, and ſubmits to the Empire or flattery of the will, it is like the hand of a diſordered Dial, that pointeth to any Figure; and it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible for that man to be free from miſtakes, who is guided and led away by his Luſts. For theſe do ſtrangely paint every object to make it love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and beautiful; ſo that when it is preſented to the underſtanding, Reaſon is like an eye that is infected with the jaundies, or that looks through a falſe Glaſs; and every thing ſeems to be of the ſame hue, and complexion, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour with the <hi>Medium.</hi> Hence it cometh to paſs mainly, that there are ſo many errors in Religion; becauſe men are willing to comply
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52826:6"/>
with thoſe doctrines which are moſt conſiſtent with their Inclinations, and moſt ſuitable to their Appetities. And this is that, I fear, which hath perſwaded ſo many to warp from the Proteſtant Religion, there being <hi>variety</hi> of ſuch <hi>Baits</hi> miniſtred by the cunning <hi>Anglers</hi> upon <hi>Tyler,</hi> as are very delightful to every mans palate and Guſto, whether they be the <hi>Clergy,</hi> or <hi>Lay-people.</hi> 1. They of the Prieſt-hood have by a thouſand ſtratagems brought it ſo to paſs, that they are made privy to all mens ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, and are become Maſters of all mens Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and make both <hi>Peaſant</hi> and <hi>Peer</hi> truc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle to their commands, and exact what Tributes they pleaſe as juſt offerings to the Church. Now by theſe means they throughly ſecure them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from that contempt and Poverty, which <hi>with us</hi> (to the ſhame of us be it ſpoken) is the common reward of many a Learned, pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and Honeſt Divine, eſpecially when we have to do with people of <hi>ſordid</hi> and <hi>degenerous</hi> principles, who neither <hi>Reſpect</hi> nor <hi>Feed</hi> the Ox that treadeth out the Corn. Now when a Religion is ſo advantageous, 'tis no wonder that there are found men, who, for their Intereſt ſake, both profeſs it themſelves, and teach it others too, though it be full of Impoſtures. We read in <hi>Act.</hi> 19. that when <hi>Demetrius</hi> and his follow-crafts men ſaw, that their Trade and their wealth was in danger, they ſtrenuouſly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd the Doctrine of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> though it want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed neither Reaſons nor Miracles to confirm it, <hi>Sirs, by this craſt, ye know, we get our wealth;</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:52826:7"/>
and that was likely to be loſt, if the world ſhould once be perſwaded to believe, <hi>that they be no Gods, which are made with hands:</hi> and therefore, for the ſake of the Silver ſhrines, they cried up <hi>Diana of the Epheſians,</hi> though it was but a ſorry Puppet which they worſhipt all this while. I am afraid, that there are many <hi>Demetriuſes</hi> now adayes, that meerly for their profit and gain, cry up <hi>Diana</hi> of the <hi>Romans</hi> alſo<hi>:</hi> For by this craft they get their Honours and Riches, and 'tis not ſtrange, that men, who aim at baſe and ſecular Ends, ſhould firſt be perſwaded to <hi>Admire,</hi> and then be concern'd to <hi>Defend</hi> a Religion that brings them ſuch a large and plentiful Dowry. The wonder is, that the <hi>Vulgar ſort</hi> ſhould ſuffer themſelves to be <hi>abus'd</hi> and <hi>cheated</hi> by men, who count <hi>gain</hi> to be Godlineſs: For, as the World now goes, people are not eaſily to be <hi>fool'd</hi> and <hi>baffled</hi> out of their <hi>Reaſon,</hi> their <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty,</hi> and their <hi>Money</hi> too: And yet, we ſee, there are ſome (and thoſe, of no mean ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction, or pitiful Parts,) who have been brought to ſubſcribe to many Deluſions, which that Church teacheth for <hi>Catholick</hi> Doctrines. But, Secondly, <hi>even theſe,</hi> I fear, do it for their <hi>Intereſt</hi> too. Though it be not for their <hi>Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Eternal</hi> Intereſt to give themſelves up to believe a Lye, yet for their <hi>Worldly</hi> and <hi>Carnal</hi> Intereſt it is; for the Intereſt of their <hi>Luſts</hi> and <hi>ſenſual Appetites,</hi> which ſome are more fond of, than of a <hi>good Conſcience.</hi> For certainly, there is not a more <hi>eaſie Religion</hi> in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52826:7"/>
the World. For, of Good Works they reckon but three ſorts, <hi>Alms, Faſting</hi> and <hi>Prayer:</hi> ſo that let a man but ſhew Mercy in ſome indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent meaſure, let him but forbear eating of fleſh when the Church bids him; let him but hear the ſervice, (though in an unknown Tongue,) and run over the <hi>Roſary,</hi> conſiſting of 150 <hi>Ave Mary's,</hi> and 15 <hi>Pater Noſters,</hi> and he need not much fear his future ſtate. So likewiſe, of Mortal Sins, they reckon but ſeven, <hi>viz.</hi> Pride, Envy, Covetouſneſs, Carnality, Gluttony, Anger, and Sloath: So that let a man forbear <hi>theſe Seven,</hi> though he commiteth <hi>Seventy times Seven more,</hi> yet to Hell he ſhall not go. Or, though he commiteth <hi>Theſe too;</hi> yet if he do but confeſs to the Prieſt once a year, or before he dieth, he is Abſolved at a cheap rate<hi>:</hi> and if he chance to expire <hi>before</hi> all his <hi>Penance be done;</hi> tis but leaving behind him a good Legacy for a Maſs, and then the pains of Purgatory ſhall not hold him long. What an <hi>Heap</hi> of <hi>Sophiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi> is here? and yet they call it <hi>Religion,</hi> and are willing to believe, that it is the <hi>only True Religion,</hi> not becauſe it is a <hi>Rational,</hi> but a <hi>Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant</hi> Model: for it ſtrains no <hi>Sinews,</hi> it breaks no <hi>bones;</hi> but ſaves them the charge of <hi>mortifying their Luſts,</hi> of <hi>crucifying their Affections, of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duing their earthly Members, of cutting off a right hand, or pulling out a right eye:</hi> and as long as things go at this rate, it is a wonder to me, that all lewd and vicious people in the world do not throw themſelvs into the boſome of that Church, where they may live as merrily as they liſt, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52826:8"/>
yet if they be not careleſs, or niggardly, or poor, may die as ſecurely and happily as they can wiſh.</p>
            <p>I have been the longer upon this Subject, becauſe I was minded to give you ſome account of that, which at this day ſeemeth ſuch a ſtrange thing, that every one is ready to lift up his hands in admiration, that when the world ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally is ſo knowing, ſome ſhould be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with, to forſake a <hi>Grave, Serious</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Religion,</hi> to embrace a <hi>Profeſſion</hi> which is made up of <hi>Fooleries, Chimaera's and Ridicules.</hi> 'Tis <hi>Intereſt</hi> many times, that opens the gate, and lets out a Renegado, or an Apoſtate. And yet.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, there is yet another account (and the <hi>weightieſt</hi> of all) which the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> gives of it in my Text; <hi>God doth</hi> many times <hi>ſend men ſtrong deluſions, that they ſhould believe a Lye.</hi> For the right underſtanding of which words two things are to be noted. 1. That the words are not ſo to be underſtood, as if God did <hi>directly infatuate</hi> the minds of men, or <hi>actually blind</hi> their underſtandings, by work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo powerfully upon them, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but Err. For as he doth not <hi>Tempt,</hi> ſo neither doth he <hi>delude</hi> any; but every man is led away by his own Luſts, and by the wiles and devices of the Prince of darkneſs; the place then is not to be underſtood in a <hi>Poſitive,</hi> but in a <hi>Negative</hi> ſenſe <hi>rather; viz.</hi> that God is many times pleaſed to <hi>permit</hi> men to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded; to deliver them up to themſelves, to let them follow their <hi>own imaginations,</hi> and to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52826:8"/>
               <hi>ſuffer them</hi> to be deceived, by letting the reins looſe to the Spirit of Error, and by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing from wicked people, though not a <hi>ſufficiency,</hi> yet that <hi>plenty</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> whereby they might have been kept out of the ſnare of the Devil. God is ſaid to have <hi>ſent</hi> an evil Spirit between <hi>Abimelech and the men of Sichem,</hi> Judg. 9. To have <hi>moved David</hi> to num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> 2 Sam. 29. To have <hi>put a lying Spirit</hi> in the mouth of <hi>Ahabs</hi> Prophets, 2 Chron. 18. To have <hi>poured</hi> out upon the Jews the Spirit of a deep Sleep, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 29. And to have <hi>given</hi> them the Spirit of Slumber, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 8. But all theſe Texts and expreſſions muſt be underſtood, of Gods <hi>Permiſſion</hi> and purpoſe of <hi>ſuffering Satan</hi> to uſe his <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Stratagems,</hi> to cloſe mens eyes, and to caſt a miſt before their underſtandings, and to draw them into Errors. And ſo here, God ſhall ſend them ſtrong De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions; that is, will <hi>ſuffer and permit the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil and his Inſtruments</hi> to delude them, that they ſhould believe a Lye. 2. It is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that when God is pleaſed to do this; it is not with an <hi>immediate deſign and direct in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,</hi> that men ſhall be deluded, that they may <hi>periſh.</hi> For he is not willing <hi>that any ſhould periſh,</hi> but that all <hi>ſhould come to Repentance.</hi> But the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaketh of the <hi>event</hi> and <hi>iſſue</hi> of things, that the wickedneſs and ingratitude of People would bring them to <hi>that paſs and upſhot,</hi> that they would believe any thing <hi>in the End,</hi> though never ſo <hi>Romantick and Fabulous:</hi> And ſo, the ſenſe of theſe words being opened,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52826:9"/>
the conſideration which now lyeth before us, is this; that however ſome are <hi>neceſſarily De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded,</hi> through their <hi>invincible ignorance;</hi> and others are <hi>willing</hi> to be Deluded for their <hi>inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt</hi> and <hi>advantage,</hi> yet that many <hi>are delivered</hi> up to <hi>ſtrong Deluſions,</hi> is a <hi>juſt judgement</hi> of God upon them, as a <hi>puniſhment of their unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs: Becauſe they received not the Love of the Truth, that they might be ſaved; for that cauſe, ſaith our Apoſtle, God ſhall ſend them ſtrong De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſions, that they ſhould believe a Lye.</hi> An ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample whereof we have in King <hi>Ahab,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18. Becauſe he would not credit the account, which <hi>Michaiah</hi> gave him concerning his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up to <hi>Ramoth Gilead,</hi> the Lord ſuffered him to be deceived, and thereby to be ſlain. <hi>The Lord ſaid, who will entice</hi> Ahab <hi>King of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>that he may go up and fall at</hi> Ramoth Gilead? <hi>And there came out a certain Spirit, and ſaid, I will entice him. I will go out, and be a lying Spirit in the mouth of all his Prophets. And the Lord ſaid, thou ſhalt entice him, and thou ſhalt alſo prevail: Go out, and do even ſo.</hi> In like manner he dealt with the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Jews, when they were in <hi>Love with Lies,</hi> and <hi>required</hi> the Prophets to <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie deceit</hi> unto them, <hi>God choſe their Deluſions,</hi> and gave them up to the ways and imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their hearts, inſomuch that the <hi>Prophets propheſied falſly, and the Prieſts did bear rule by their means,</hi> and (which is obſervable) the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple did <hi>Love to have it ſo,</hi> Jer. 5. 31. And to the like purpoſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of thoſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52826:9"/>
who held the Truth in unrighteouſneſs; <hi>becauſe that when they knew God, they glorified him not as God, neither were thankful, they became vain in their imaginations, and their fooliſh heart was darkened; ſo that profeſſing themſelves to be wiſe, they became fools;</hi> and were given <hi>over to a Reprobate mind, and to be without underſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this conſideration, that God doth many times, in <hi>Judgement upon wicked people, ſend them ſtrong Deluſions, that they ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a Lye,</hi> ſerveth to theſe two good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes (that I may not mention any more:)</p>
            <p n="1">1. It diſcovers unto us the Reaſon, why it is ſuch an hard and very difficult matter, to reclaim people that have <hi>once wilfully revolted from the Truth.</hi> Every Age hath found it true by ſad experience, that it is much more eaſie to convert that perſon from the Error of his way, who hath been <hi>bred up</hi> in Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from his <hi>Youth,</hi> than to <hi>reduce</hi> that man who hath <hi>turned aſide</hi> either to <hi>Atheiſm,</hi> or to <hi>Idolatry,</hi> and <hi>Superſtition,</hi> albeit he may have been inſtructed out of the Scriptures from his Childhood. Such a one ſinneth againſt grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter light of Conſcience, and ſo is infinitely more Criminal, in <hi>ſhutting his own eyes,</hi> than he who never had his <hi>eyes open,</hi> nor had a Torch held out unto him to find out the True way. Queſtionleſs a man may ſin away Gods Grace by degrees; and of all ſorts of Sinners, the Apoſtate ſeemeth to take the <hi>Largeſt ſtep</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards it: and therefore the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Renegado</hi>'s from the Truth, tells us, <hi>Heb,</hi> 6. 4, 5, 6.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52826:10"/>
               <hi>That it is impoſſible for thoſe, who were once en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightened, and have taſted of the Heavenly gift, and were made partakers of the Holy Ghoſt, and have taſted the good Word of God, and the powers of the World to come, if they ſhall fall away, to renew them again unto Repentance.</hi> For if any man <hi>quencheth</hi> the Spirit, <hi>it is he.</hi> If any man <hi>treadeth under foot the Son of God,</hi> it is <hi>he.</hi> If any man <hi>counteth the Blood of the Covenant an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holy thing,</hi> it is <hi>he.</hi> If any man <hi>doth deſpite unto the Spirit of Grace,</hi> it is <hi>he:</hi> And after ſo many ſins, ſo much obſtinacy, and ſo much ſtanding out againſt the clamours and ſnub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bings of <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Enlightned</hi> Conſcience, to recover that man out of his Apoſtacy, by the graveſt <hi>Counſels,</hi> by the moſt pathetical <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations,</hi> or by the ſtrongeſt and moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing <hi>Arguments,</hi> though it be not <hi>abſolutely impoſſible,</hi> yet it is next door unto it; and the Reaſon of it, is here in my Text; becauſe he loved not the Truth, therefore hath <hi>God ſent him ſtrong Deluſions, that he ſhould believe a Lye.</hi> Let him therefore <hi>that ſtandeth</hi> (as he valueth the favour of God, the comforts, and fellowſhip of the Spirit, and the Eternal intereſt and felicity of his own Soul, let him) <hi>take heed leſt he fall,</hi> 1 Cor. 10. 12.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This Conſideration of <hi>Gods ſending ſome men ſtrong Deluſions,</hi> ſerveth to clear up that, which in our Age, ſeemeth to be a Miracle of wonders; how it cometh to paſs, that many <hi>famous</hi> and <hi>learned Divines,</hi> in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> have both believed thoſe things <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:52826:10"/>
and <hi>obtruded</hi> them upon <hi>others</hi> alſo, as ſo many <hi>ſound</hi> and <hi>Catholick Truths,</hi> which even <hi>unskilful Men</hi> and <hi>Ideots in our Communion,</hi> can diſcover to be meer deluſions, or falſhoods, as it were, of yeſterday. I remember, <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaid, <hi>Sapientis eſt, nihil admirari,</hi> That a Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man will wonder at nothing; and, I think, we need not wonder at this thing, <hi>if it be ſo;</hi> but rather we may <hi>make</hi> it a <hi>Queſtion, whether it be ſo indeed?</hi> Whether they have believed thoſe points <hi>themſelves,</hi> which they have offered <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us,</hi> as Articles of Faith? St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> tells of <hi>Varro,</hi> that learned Pagan, that he affirmed, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug. de Civ. Dei, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 31.</note> 
               <hi>That many things in Religion were true, which it was not fit that the Vulgar ſort ſhould know; and on the other hand, that tho ſome things were falſe, yet it was not convenient for the common People to believe otherwiſe.</hi> And ſo he tells us of <hi>Scaevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la</hi> the <hi>Roman High-Prieſt in thoſe times</hi> of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſme, that <hi>Expedire exiſtimavit, falli in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligione Civitates. He thought it very expedient for</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>De Civ. Dei, lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>Cities to be deceived in their Religion.</hi> And ſome others too (eſpecially among the old Greeks) have ſpoken to the ſame purpoſe. And it is not impoſſible, but ſome <hi>Chriſtian Romanes</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid. Joſeph. cont. Appion. lib.</hi> 2.</note> may have thought, as <hi>Varro</hi> and <hi>Scaevola</hi> did of old, that for certain Reaſons the Vulgar ought to be made believe many things, tho they be not true. I would ſtrain my Charity to think well of the worſt; but yet I cannot for all my Charity but <hi>fear</hi> at leaſt, that ſome Popiſh Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines have acted quite againſt their own <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,</hi> and uſed indirect Arts to gull the reſt of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52826:11"/>
the World, teaching ſuch Doctrines for True, which <hi>they themſelves could</hi> not but know to be <hi>falſe,</hi> and I ſhall give you two inſtances to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm my opinion, that it may not ſeem to be an uncharitable <hi>conjecture only.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When they procured a Commiſſion from King <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Spain,</hi> to ſearch for all ſorts of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Books,</hi> and to purge out of them thoſe paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages which made for the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and to note thoſe paſſages in a Book by it ſelf, called the <hi>Expurgatory Index,</hi> there were notable <hi>Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> inſerted in the <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> that the Book ſo compiled ſhould not in <hi>any wiſe be made pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Vide Diploma praefix. Ind. Exp. Edit. Belg.</note> but <hi>commited to the truſt of ſome certain faithful Prelates;</hi> and that thoſe Prelates ſhould not communicate the matter <hi>to any,</hi> but ſuch as they ſhould judge to be <hi>truſty,</hi> and by them to be <hi>kept very cloſe,</hi> and not ſo much as the ſight of one Copy to be imparted unto others, tho they were Catholicks. Now was not this <hi>acting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Conſcience?</hi> For if they intended to deal fairly and upon the Square, why was this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivance to be kept under the <hi>Seal of Secrecy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again; When the Cenſors of <hi>Doway</hi> were upon promoting of this <hi>deſign</hi> of <hi>purging Books,</hi> and did light upon ſeveral <hi>ancient</hi> Writers (and perticularly upon <hi>Bertram,</hi> who lived within nine hundred years after Chriſt, and wrote things deſtructive of Tranſubſtantiation) they reſolved together not to burn thoſe Books, but either to bear with their Errors, or to <hi>exte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miate</hi> them, or to <hi>excuſe</hi> them, and to give them as <hi>kind</hi> a ſenſe as could be; and if the ſhoo
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52826:11"/>
pinched too much, than their <hi>laſt refuge</hi> was roundly and manfully to <hi>deny the matter</hi> in their diſputations with their Adverſaries: this is the Engliſh of their own words, in their <hi>Cenſure</hi> of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 13. <hi>Ind. Exp. Edit. Belg.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bertram</hi>'s Book. And if this be not in plain Engliſh down right <hi>diſhoneſty,</hi> we are yet to ſeek; what the <hi>Nature</hi> of <hi>Cheating</hi> is.</p>
            <p>From theſe two Inſtances it doth appear, that there is reaſon enough for us to <hi>ſuſpect</hi> at leaſt, that they have acted <hi>craftily,</hi> and <hi>againſt the light</hi> of their own Conſciences; and ſo, it is very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable that they do <hi>ſtill,</hi> and that they may know <hi>themſelves</hi> the falſhood of thoſe things, which they would fain have us to believe, and perhaps for <hi>Varro</hi>'s and <hi>Scaevola</hi>'s reaſon, becauſe it is fit ſometimes the People ſhould be <hi>deceived</hi> in their Religion, for <hi>peace and quietneſs ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet, What if the Rulers of theſe People be of <hi>the ſame Faith</hi> with their Vaſſals? it is no ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the truth of their Creed, becauſe <hi>great</hi> and <hi>learned Men</hi> have believed it, for <hi>great</hi> and <hi>learned</hi> Men may be, and have been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. That great Philoſopher <hi>Zeno,</hi> did que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, whether there was any ſuch thing as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in the world; but what authority is this for <hi>me</hi> to disbeleive my own eyes? And <hi>Scipio Tettus</hi> was ſuch a Fool, that he denied the being of God, and ſet up a School of Atheiſm, and died a Martyr for Atheiſm, and clapt his hands too in the very flames. Now all that we can col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect from theſe and the like inſtances, is, that Man is a moſt <hi>ſenſeleſs Creature,</hi> when God gives him up to his own <hi>conduct</hi> and <hi>management,</hi> eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52826:12"/>
if he be blinded too by him, that <hi>ruleth in darkneſs. Magnus Deus eſt error,</hi> as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid, Error is a God, which the moſt admired <hi>Sophies</hi> are ready to adore, when the God of Truth, Righteouſneſs, and Peace ſhall leave them <hi>to themſelves,</hi> and commit them to their <hi>own hands.</hi> And that this is uſual, the Inſtances are <hi>too many</hi> to be inſiſted on, and the thing is <hi>too common</hi> to be wondered at. And ſo the firſt thing I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded is made good, that many people are led away by ſtrong deluſions, to believe that which is a manifeſt and notorious lie, and how this cometh to paſs: Partly by the power of Mens <hi>Education,</hi> partly by the efficacy of their <hi>Luſts;</hi> but chiefly by the <hi>Juſtice of God,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by puniſhing them for their darling wickedneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; <hi>for this cauſe God doth ſend them ſtrong Deluſions that they ſhould believe a Lie.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:52826:12"/>
            <head>ANCIENT and MODERN DELUSIONS, Diſcourſed of in three SERMONS Upon 2 THES. 2. 11.</head>
            <head>SERM. II.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2. THES. 2. 11.</bibl>
               <q>And for this cauſe God ſhall ſend them ſtrong Delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, that they ſhould believe a Lye.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE ſecond conſideration now fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, that notwithſtanding thoſe great Evidences which have been given on the behalf of Truth, yet multitudes of ſilly people are very fond of deluſions and lyes ſtill; nay, even ſuch as are of the ſame, or of the like Nature, with thoſe Deluſions which St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of here, which he ſayeth were to be ſent upon that Generation, as a curſe and Judgement upon them, becauſe they loved not the Truth, that they might be ſaved.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:52826:13"/>
In the handling of this matter I muſt of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity obſerve this Method; to ſhew you what thoſe Pretences were which prevailed in the <hi>very firſt</hi> ages of Chriſtianity: Then, that many pretences which are in vogue now do <hi>reſemble</hi> and <hi>come very near</hi> to thoſe which were broached <hi>in the beginning</hi> by damned Sedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers; and laſtly, that theſe are <hi>meer Deluſions</hi> and <hi>Lyes,</hi> how ſpecious ſoever they may appear unto the vulgar.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then it is obſervable and very certain, that in the moſt Primitive Times of the Church, many Impoſtors did pretend to an <hi>Infallible Spirit.</hi> This is clear to any man that hath but enquired into the Hiſtory and condition of that Age wherein the Apoſtles of Chriſt lived. For <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorcerer (of whom we read <hi>Act.</hi> 8. and whom the Ancients called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the Eldeſt Son of the Devil)</hi> pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that he was <hi>that Divine Being,</hi> which fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed both the <hi>Angelical</hi> and <hi>Viſible</hi> world. He perſwaded many to believe, <hi>that he was the great power of God;</hi> or (as it may be rendred) that he was that <hi>Power, Numen,</hi> or <hi>Divine Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie,</hi> which is called <hi>Great.</hi> He pretended to be <hi>more</hi> than <hi>Gods Vicar</hi> upon Earth; for he gave out, that he was <hi>the very God,</hi> that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiph. Haereſ.</hi> 21. <hi>Iren. l.</hi> 1 <hi>c.</hi> 20. <hi>Cyril. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tech.</hi> 5. <hi>Iuſtin. Dial. in Tryph. Euſeb. Hiſt. Eccl. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</note> upon Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> as <hi>the Father;</hi> that he was the Chriſt, that afterwards converſed with the Jews <hi>as the Son;</hi> and that he was the Holy Ghoſt, that at laſt deſcended as the <hi>Paraclete, or</hi> promiſed <hi>Comforter. Euſebius</hi> tells us, that he had a <hi>Demon</hi> alwayes attending on him, which
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52826:13"/>
was called the <hi>Virtus</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, whereby he <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Quod &amp; de Marco. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not. Iren. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> wrought ſuch ſeeming Miracles, that he was worſhipped as the <hi>Supream</hi> and <hi>Sovereign De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ity,</hi> and it appears by the joynt teſtimonies of <hi>Tertullian, Juſtin Martyr,</hi> and other the moſt <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Tertul. Apol. c.</hi> 13 <hi>Iuſtin. Apol.</hi> 2. <hi>Iren. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 20. <hi>Cyril. Catech.</hi> 5.</note> ancient Writers of the Church, that <hi>Claudius</hi> the Emperor erected a great Statue in honour of him, with this Inſcription upon it, <hi>Simoni Deo ſancto,</hi> to the Holy God <hi>Simon.</hi> Some lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Divines do conceive, that <hi>this was</hi> that Man of Sin, of whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, in this 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 4. <hi>That he oppoſed and exalted himſelf above all that is called God, or that is worſhipped,</hi> &amp;c. This is certain, that his Followers pretended to the <hi>moſt perfect and certain knowledge</hi> of Gods Will, inſomuch that they <hi>deſpiſed</hi> the Apoſtles themſelves, as much <hi>inferiour</hi> to them in under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Divine Myſteries. And <hi>Epipha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> relates, that when the Church appealed to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiph. lib</hi> 1. <hi>Haereſ.</hi> 14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 34. <hi>Iren. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>c</hi> 2.</note> the <hi>Writings</hi> of the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> they urged the authority of a <hi>more infallible Tradition,</hi> and affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med themſelves to be <hi>wiſer</hi> than the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and to be Preachers of <hi>greater Truths,</hi> than ever the Apoſtles were acquainted with. Theſe were thoſe <hi>falſe Prophets,</hi> which our Saviour foretold would come, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. 15. He called them falſe <hi>Prophets,</hi> not becauſe they pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>foretel</hi> future events, but becauſe they <hi>falſly</hi> pretended to <hi>Divine Inſpiration,</hi> and to an <hi>Infallible Spirit.</hi> Theſe are they which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, were puffed up with a profeſſion of <hi>Science, falſly ſo called,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. Theſe were they, whom he called <hi>falſe Apoſtles, deceitful</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:52826:14"/>
               <hi>workers, transforming themſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 11. 13. And theſe are they, againſt whom he cautioneth the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> in this Chapter, that they ſhould not be ſhak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en in mind <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. by any <hi>pretences of the Spirit,</hi> by a ſhew of <hi>Inſpiration, Immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Revelation,</hi> and <hi>Infallible Knowledge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now by what hath been ſpoken you may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily obſerve, that the <hi>Fundamental</hi> and <hi>Grand</hi> Pretence, upon which thoſe <hi>monſtrous Hereticks</hi> went in the Apoſtles Times, was <hi>This,</hi> that their Maſter was <hi>the Divine Oracle,</hi> the great Teacher of all Truth; and that they themſelves <hi>by being his Diſciples</hi> had this Priviledge <hi>above</hi> other men, to be <hi>divinely</hi> and <hi>immediately inſpired,</hi> ſo that they neither <hi>did</hi> nor <hi>could</hi> be miſtaken in their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion. Like unto this is the <hi>modern</hi> pretence tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the <hi>Infallibility</hi> of the <hi>Biſhop</hi> and Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> What the <hi>old Gnoſticks</hi> did claim by and under <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> that do the <hi>new Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts</hi> claim by and under <hi>Simon Peter,</hi> that their Teachers and Guides <hi>cannot Err.</hi> Tho for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove fourteen hundred years together the Popes judgement was not counted infallible, yet now it is an undoubted Article, and the <hi>Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</hi> Tenet among them (eſpecially among the <hi>Jeſuites)</hi> that their Great Pontifex hath this <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative</hi> above <hi>all Councils,</hi> that <hi>in his quae ad fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem pertinent nullo caſu errare poſſit,</hi> as Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi> affirms; in things pertaining to the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellarm. de Rom. Pontif. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 3.</note> Faith <hi>he cannot erre</hi> in any caſe.</p>
            <p>Now that this is a meer <hi>Deluſion</hi> and a noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious <hi>lie.</hi> Our Writers have uſed ſeveral effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52826:14"/>
wayes to prove. But becauſe I do not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to wade up to the neck in ſuch a ſenſeleſs Controverſie, I ſhall take this as a ready and ſatisfactory courſe, by ſhewing you briefly how Contradictory the ſenſe of one Pope hath been to the judgement of another; and ſo by ſetting them together againſt themſelves, it will ſoon appear what a vain and ſilly pretence, that of their <hi>Infallibility</hi> is. To begin: Saint <hi>Peter</hi> (as they reckon) was the firſt Biſhop of <hi>Rome:</hi> and he has left that behind him which doth blaſt the Infallibility of his pretended Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors; for he declared the King to have <hi>no Superior:</hi> Though he himſelf was ſo great an Apoſtle, and all Kings then were <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Infidels,</hi> yet he taught us to ſubmit our ſelves to every ordinance, and to the <hi>King</hi> as <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 13. But <hi>Pius</hi> the <hi>4th.</hi> claimed that at the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> which <hi>Engenius</hi> the <hi>4th.</hi> had lately defined at the Council of <hi>Florence,</hi> that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> holdeth the Primacy over the whole World (Kings and Emperors not excepted.) And this they are ſo fond of ſtill, that whoſoever among us ſhall <hi>ex animo,</hi> take the <hi>Oath of Supremacy,</hi> muſt lie under a Curſe as an <hi>Heretick</hi> and an <hi>Apoſtate</hi> from the Catholick See. Again; the Title of Univerſal Paſtorſhip over all the <hi>Biſhops</hi> in the World, all the Popes have claimed ſince the days of <hi>Boniface</hi> the Third; and yet <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the Great, while he was Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> declaimed horribly againſt it, and in divers of his Epiſtles, calls it a Title full of <hi>Novelty, Vanity,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:52826:15"/>
               <hi>Blaſphemy, Pride, Madneſs,</hi> and <hi>Wickedneſs,</hi> and ſaid, that it was a <hi>Preparative to the Times of Anti-chriſt.</hi> Again, this buſineſs of Infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which is now one of the <hi>choiceſt</hi> feathers in the Old mans Cap, was formerly account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by themſelves, as a <hi>New-nothing.</hi> For about 250 years ſince (no longer ago) <hi>Adrian</hi> the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellarm. de Rom. Pontif. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> ſixth did ingeniouſly and honeſtly declare, that the Pope might not only <hi>Err,</hi> but might be an <hi>Heretick</hi> too, and might <hi>teach Hereſie,</hi> and that ſome Popes have, <hi>de facto,</hi> done ſo. And to make good what this Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> ſaid, it is further obſervable, that <hi>Liberius</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed the <hi>Arian Hereſie,</hi> and the thing is ſo certain, that Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelf doth confeſs it, and produceth many Authorities to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hierom. in Catalog. Ballarm. de Rom. Pont. lib.</hi> 4 <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> prove it. Moreover, <hi>Honorius</hi> the firſt held, that there was but one Will in Chriſt; and <hi>Vigilius</hi> denied, that Chriſt had two natures; and <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> the ſecond was a Photinian; and <hi>Marcellinus</hi> was <hi>more</hi> than an Heretick, for <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Melch. Canus lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Gratian diſt.</hi> 19. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>Council. Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueſ. Tert. adv. Prax.</hi>
               </note> he <hi>Apoſtatiz'd</hi> to <hi>Heatheniſm,</hi> and ſacrificed to <hi>Heathen Idols;</hi> and <hi>Zepherinus</hi> embraced the Propheſies of <hi>Montanus;</hi> and <hi>Rhenanus</hi> himſelf, in his Annotations upon <hi>Tertullian,</hi> notes it on the Margin, as a thing to be obſerved, <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Romanus Montanizat,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is turned Montaniſt. And yet Montaniſm, and Arianiſm, and Photinianiſm, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sects I have named, were juſtly reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by ſucceeding Popes, as ſo many <hi>Heretical Profeſſions and Factions,</hi> which yet theſe their Predeceſſors did embrance notwithſtanding. And
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52826:15"/>
ſince this is Pope againſt Pope, one contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicting and condemning the other, and that in things pertaining to the Faith; How is it like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and poſſible, that every one of them could be in the Right? Further yet; two things are obſerved of Pope <hi>Galaſius</hi> the firſt, that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Magdeb. Cent</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>de Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Dom. &amp; cap.</hi> 10. <hi>in vita Gelaſii.</hi>
               </note> he flatly affirmed <hi>the Elements in the Sacrament to remain in their own Nature Bread and Wine;</hi> and that he <hi>called it a piece of Sacriledge, to adminiſter the Bread without the Wine:</hi> But how irreconcileable his Doctrine is with that of latter Popes, who teach Tranſubſtantion, and half Communion, any man may ſee with half an Eye. Again, <hi>Caeleſtine</hi> the Third, taught <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Alphonſ. de Caſtro lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> that Marriage was void and null, if either the Wife or the Husband became an Heretick; and yet the quite contrary was taught by his immediate Succeſſor <hi>Innocent</hi> the Third, and ſo it has continued to be taught by the reſt of the Popes ſince. Further yet: The Papiſts are pleas'd to call <hi>Mr. Calvin</hi> an Heretick, for af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming, that the ſouls of Saints departed ſhall not enjoy the <hi>perfect</hi> viſion of God until the Reſurrection. Yet this Doctrine was taught by Pope <hi>John</hi> the <hi>22th.</hi> but (to ſee the Infallibility of theſe Men) ſome ſay, that <hi>John</hi> himſelf recanted this before his death; however it is certain, that the contrary was defined by <hi>Benedict,</hi> the Twelfth, <hi>Johns</hi> next Succeſſor; and ſo the Popes teach ſtill, that ſuch Souls are <hi>perfectly</hi> happy upon their departure; and this is the fundamental Principle upon which their Invocations of Saints ſtandeth; and were
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52826:16"/>
it not for that, I believe <hi>John</hi>'s opinion would have been received as a <hi>certain Truth.</hi> But what ſhall we ſay of <hi>John</hi> the <hi>23th.</hi> who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the Articles of Eternal Life, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the Body? And for his Hereſie was accuſed, and condemned by their own Council of <hi>Conſtance?</hi> Either he, or other Popes were <hi>groſsly</hi> miſtaken; and which of the two is moſt likely, we leave to themſelves to diſpute it out.</p>
            <p>To theſe I might add many inſtances more; as, that <hi>John</hi> the 12th. <hi>ordained a Deacon in a ſtable,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Magdeb. Cent.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>drank healths to the Devils, and called up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Devils for help when he was at Dice;</hi> that there was an Age (as <hi>Platina</hi> tells us) when <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Plat. in vit. Steph.</hi> 6.</note> 'twas uſual with Popes to make <hi>void</hi> all that their <hi>Predeceſſors</hi> had done; that, when <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſus</hi> was dead, <hi>Stephen</hi> the <hi>6th.</hi> made his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be taken out of the <hi>Grave,</hi> cauſed ſome <note place="margin">Ballarm.</note> of his fingers to be cut off, and his Carcaſe to be thrown into the River; that then Pope <hi>Romanus</hi> was ſet up, who condemned the Acts of <hi>Stephen;</hi> and then came <hi>Sergius</hi> the 3<hi>d.</hi> who ratified what <hi>Stephen</hi> had done, and nulled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the Acts of <hi>Formoſus.</hi> I might inſtance alſo in another of their pretended Infallible Oracles, I mean that <hi>Female Pope,</hi> who turned St. <hi>Peters</hi> into a <hi>groaning</hi> Chair, and was delivered of a Popeling; and ſo cozened the <hi>whole Church</hi> and <hi>her ſelf too</hi> (notwithſtanding her Infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;) but as to this, it will be ſaid, that it was not <hi>Error in Capite,</hi> a judicial Error, but a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal ſlip only (an hurt in the Elbow or the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52826:16"/>
Shin) or elſe they will deny, that there was ever ſuch a Pope, and with them it is a Rule, that <hi>Fortiter mentiri,</hi> to Lye <hi>ſtrenuouſly,</hi> and to <hi>ſwear to it,</hi> for the ſake of the Catholick cauſe, is not only <hi>pardonable,</hi> but <hi>meritorous</hi> too. I ſhall only add (what is very well known) that <hi>Sixtus</hi> the <hi>5th.</hi> ſet forth a Latine Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of the Bible, and curſed all that would not uſe <hi>that;</hi> and after him came <hi>Clement</hi> the <hi>8th.</hi> and ſet forth another and different Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation, and curſed all that would not uſe <hi>that;</hi> ſo that let the Romaniſts turn themſelves which way they pleaſe, they are all accurſed and damned, if it be ſo that their Popes be indeed Infallible.</p>
            <p>But 'tis a wonder, that any <hi>Learned</hi> perſon ſhould be of that opinion of men, who have been ſo vicious, ſo ridiculous, and ſo inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with themſelves, that the <hi>Italians them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> have made them the Subjects of the bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt <hi>Paſquils and Satyrs:</hi> only I do remember (what a Learned Writer hath obſerved of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neas</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Biſhop Taylor lib. of Proph. Sect.</hi> 7.</note> 
               <hi>Silvius)</hi> that before he came to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to the Popedome, he <hi>laughed</hi> at the conceit of the Popes Infallibility; and the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why ſome did ſet him above Councils, was this (as he ingeniouſly confeſt,) becauſe the Pope had the diſpoſal of all Spiritual Preferments, which Councils had not, and ſo the thing fairly ends, that 'tis not the Love of <hi>Truth,</hi> but the Love of <hi>Intereſt,</hi> which has made men to ſweat, to defend this pretence of Infallibility. A pretence which I have been the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52826:17"/>
longer upon, becauſe it is the grand Deluſion on which many others are built; and though many, who dare not believe their own <hi>Senſes,</hi> are ſo ſenſeleſs and ſottiſh, as to believe this <hi>fancy,</hi> yet I conſider, that thouſands have been juſtly given up to believe a Lye. That great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor <hi>Montanus</hi> pretended that he was the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clete, or Comforter that was promiſed; and that Deluſion prevailed ſo, that the Acute and Learned <hi>Tertullian,</hi> himſelf was at <hi>laſt</hi> perſwaded of the Truth of it. Though it be a <hi>dangerous,</hi> yet 'tis no <hi>New thing</hi> for the <hi>worſt</hi> of men to ſay, they are Infallible. Thoſe falſe Prophets, and falſe Teachers, who ſeduced the World in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles days, pretended the ſame thing; and it was the grand Deluſion which the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous God delivered them and their follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers up to believe, becauſe they loved not the Truth.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Another thing obſervable of thoſe firſt Hereticks is, that they taught the <hi>worſhip of Images.</hi> S. <hi>John</hi> cautioned his little Children, to <hi>keep themſelves from Idols,</hi> 1 Joh. 5. 21. And S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake of ſome <hi>Idolaters</hi> that were in the World in <hi>his</hi> days, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 10. Now by theſe are to be underſtood, not <hi>only</hi> thoſe who worſhipped the <hi>Pagan Deities,</hi> but thoſe alſo who worſhipped <hi>Pictures,</hi> whether of God, or of Chriſt, or of Men. And that ſuch there were in thoſe firſt times is very clear out of the Writings of many Ancient Doctors in the Church; and though they called themſelves <hi>Chriſtians</hi> as the ſincere Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52826:17"/>
of the Goſpel were called, yet were they condemned, and preſcribed by the Church, as vile and abominable <hi>Hereticks.</hi> Such were the <hi>Cerinthians,</hi> who boaſted of their immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Revelations, and yet honoured the Picture of <hi>Judas</hi> himſelf, becauſe he was the <hi>occaſion</hi> of Chriſts death. <hi>Simon Magus</hi> (of whom I ſpake <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiph. Haereſ.</hi> 21. <hi>Iren. l.</hi> 1 <hi>c.</hi> 20. <hi>Auguſtinus. Euſebius.</hi>
               </note> before) delivered an Effigies of himſelf to his Followers in the ſhape of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and another of his Strumpet <hi>Helena</hi> in the ſhape of <hi>Miner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va;</hi> and his Diſciples by <hi>his directions</hi> worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped theſe with <hi>proſtrations,</hi> with <hi>incenſe,</hi> with <hi>meat</hi> and <hi>drink-Offerings.</hi> In like manner the <hi>Carpocratians</hi> had the Pictures of <hi>Chriſt</hi> and of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iren. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> 
               <hi>Paul,</hi> and of others, to which they gave <hi>religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous worſhip;</hi> and by ſo doing did conceive, that they greatly honoured <hi>Chriſt himſelf</hi> and his Apoſtles. Now all theſe <hi>poyſonous Branches</hi> of Idolatry proceeded from one <hi>bitter Root,</hi> that wicked Sorcerer, who was the Author of all <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyril. Cat.</hi> 5. <hi>Vide Ouzel. in Min. Faelic.</hi> p. 54.</note> Hereſies: And the learned Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> is of opinion, that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> pointeth to <hi>theſe Impoſtors, Rom.</hi> 1. 23. where he ſaith, that <hi>they changed the Glory of the incorruptible God, into an Image made like unto a corruptible man,</hi> for they ſuppoſed, that <hi>God himſelf</hi> was adored and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped <hi>in and by</hi> theſe Images and Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. Like unto this old abominable and heretical Practice is the modern Practice of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> in worſhipping the Pictures of the <hi>Perſons in the Holy Trinity,</hi> of the <hi>Holy Virgin, and of the Apoſtles and other Saints:</hi> And tho they would come off with a <hi>nice</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:52826:18"/>
and <hi>fooliſh diſtinction</hi> between <hi>Latria</hi> and <hi>Dulia</hi> (which yet their Writers do not throughly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in;) yet ſuppoſe they do <hi>not pretend</hi> to give Divine worſhip to the <hi>Images themſelves,</hi> but to the <hi>Prototypes,</hi> that is to God and to Chriſt, who are thus Repreſented, <hi>this</hi> is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry groſs deluſion and <hi>a Lie, in the Scripture ſenſe of the Word,</hi> that is, down right <hi>Idolatry.</hi> For they, who worſhipped the golden Calf in the Wilderneſs, are called by the <hi>Apoſtle Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 7. and yet they were not ſo <hi>ſottiſh</hi> as to think, that the <hi>Image</hi> which they had juſt formed <hi>with their hands</hi> was the very <hi>True God;</hi> but looked upon it as the <hi>Symbol</hi> of Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, and worſhipt it as <hi>Gods Repreſentative;</hi> and their Worſhip was <hi>ultimately</hi> directed, not to the <hi>Calf,</hi> but to <hi>God himſelf</hi> by the Image, and under that Similitude; and ſo they were guilty of Idolatry in the <hi>Manner,</hi> tho not in the <hi>Object</hi> of their worſhip; for they worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped the <hi>True God</hi> after a <hi>Falſe way.</hi> And in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed this was the <hi>Idolatry</hi> of the very <hi>Pagans.</hi> For tho many of the <hi>vulgar</hi> ſort among them <hi>terminated</hi> their worſhip in the <hi>Images themſelves,</hi> yet the <hi>wiſer</hi> ſort did conceive and prefer, that they worſhipped the <hi>Great God</hi> by their Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and not the Images themſelves. So <hi>Celſus</hi> declared in his Diſputations with <hi>Origen,</hi> that he was no better than a <hi>perfect Fool, that looked upon thoſe things (things of Wood and Stone, of Braſs and Gold)</hi> to be Gods and not rather as <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Origen. cont. Celſ.</hi> l. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Images</hi> of the Gods. And the Pagans in <hi>Arno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> profeſt that they worſhipp'd Statues, only <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Arnob.</hi> l. 6.</note>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:52826:18"/>
becauſe <hi>through them</hi> honor is given to the <hi>Gods,</hi> whereas the <hi>Images themſelves</hi> were wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipt only for their <hi>Dedication,</hi> and <hi>Relation</hi> ſake unto the Deity. This was the Plea of the <hi>Heathens,</hi> and this is the Plea of the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> ſo that either <hi>they</hi> are guilty of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry, or elſe neither <hi>Jews</hi> nor <hi>Heathens</hi> were ever guilty of it: And whatever evaſions <hi>they</hi> make uſe of to excuſe <hi>their Image</hi> worſhip, the ſame ſhifts any Learned man, may uſe to excuſe the <hi>Idolatries</hi> of the <hi>firſt Seducers,</hi> the <hi>Simoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> the <hi>Cerinthians,</hi> the <hi>Carpocratians,</hi> and the <hi>Collyridians</hi> too, who offered up <hi>Cakes to the Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Mary</hi>'s Image. For all theſe did believe, that this Worſhip and Honour did <hi>chiefly</hi> and <hi>ultimately</hi> redound to the Honour of God; and this was a Deluſion, and a Lie, which they were delivered up to believe; and I wiſh ſome pretended Catholicks had not raked up the ſame Deluſions out of theſe Old Hereticks Graves.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Of whom it is yet further obſervable, that they taught the <hi>Adoration</hi> and <hi>Invocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Heavenly Spirits,</hi> as <hi>Mediators</hi> between them and the great God. This is expreſly recorded by <hi>Epiphanius</hi> of <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiph. Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ.</hi> 21.</note> that he taught his followers, <hi>that no man could be ſaved, unleſs he did offer up Sacrifice to the great Parent of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe, by thoſe Principalities, and Powers, and Intelligences which are above.</hi> And queſtionleſs, this is that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>worſhipping of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> which S. <hi>Paul</hi> condemns, 2 <hi>Col.</hi> 18. <hi>Let no man beguile you of your Reward, in a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:52826:19"/>
               <hi>humility, and worſhipping of Angels.</hi> That is, let no man rob you of that which is the <hi>peculiar</hi> honour of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> (who call upon God through the <hi>Eternal Word onely,</hi> let no man beguile you out of that way) by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading you to an <hi>uncommanded</hi> piece of humility, to go to God by <hi>many Mediators</hi> and <hi>Advocates,</hi> as if it were <hi>too much</hi> confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and rudeneſs to direct your Prayers <hi>immediately</hi> unto the Father of Spirits: And in order hereunto, take heed, that ye be not tempted to worſhip and invocate the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> who are thought to be Gods <hi>Miniſters of State,</hi> to carry his <hi>Commands</hi> down unto Men, and to convey mens <hi>Prayers</hi> up unto God. This was certainly the fooliſh and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Practice of many deluded people in thoſe dayes; and very like unto this is the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions and unlawful Practice of many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded wretches in our days, who do not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pray to their <hi>Guardian Angel</hi> to <hi>defend</hi> and to <hi>direct</hi> them, but alſo to S. <hi>Michael</hi> the Arch-Angel, and to all the (ſuppoſed) <hi>Nine</hi> orders of <hi>Bleſſed Spirits;</hi> and to the Souls of <hi>Patriarchs</hi> and <hi>Prophets,</hi> of <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Martyrs,</hi> and to the <hi>Spirits</hi> of all Saints de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, to be their <hi>Mediators</hi> and <hi>Interceſſors</hi> at the Throne of Grace. But this is a meer Deluſion and a Lye, though they believe it to be an Act of great Piety and Devotion: For <hi>Abraham is ignorant of us, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgeth</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63. 16.</note> 
               <hi>us not:</hi> Nor doth our Saviour himſelf ſend us to God any <hi>other</hi> way but by <hi>him,</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:52826:19"/>
nor direct us to pray in any other <hi>Name</hi> but in <hi>his;</hi> nor doth the Scriptures own any <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 5.</note> more then <hi>one Mediatour between God</hi> and Men, the <hi>Man Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> To addreſs ones ſelf to a plurality of <hi>Inferior Spirits,</hi> and <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate Mediatours,</hi> is down right <hi>Heatheniſm,</hi> which Religion Chriſt came to <hi>deſtroy,</hi> and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 6. 7.</note> forbad us to Pray, <hi>as the Heathens did;</hi> and ſo we are not only to forbear all <hi>Battologies</hi> and <hi>vain Repetitions,</hi> which the Pagans <hi>uſed;</hi> but alſo we muſt declaim all <hi>Plurality of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſors,</hi> which the Pagans <hi>believed.</hi> And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe this is a uſeful ſpeculation, I would ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve unto you theſe four things, touching the Religion of the <hi>Old Heathens,</hi> much where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of theſe Gnoſticks in my Text did inſert into <hi>their</hi> Religion, and upon which they <hi>ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> their Practice of worſhipping, and praying to <hi>Daemons</hi> and <hi>Inviſible Spirits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. They believed, as we all do, that there is <hi>but one Supreme, Sovereign</hi> and <hi>Independent Diety,</hi> which preſideth over the whole World, and ordereth all things in Heaven and Earth. Yet nevertheleſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They believed, that between God and Men there were vaſt numbers of <hi>Inferior Deities,</hi> and <hi>Deified Souls</hi> (as the Romaniſts reckon great multitudes of <hi>Canonized and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted Saints)</hi> to whom the great God did commit the care of Men, and the Government <note place="margin">See Dr. Cud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worths Intel. Syſtem.</note> of the World.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They believed (as the Romaniſts do al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo) that ſince God was a Being of moſt tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52826:20"/>
               <hi>perfection,</hi> it was not <hi>manners</hi> for men to addreſs themſelves unto <hi>him,</hi> but by the <hi>favour</hi> and <hi>means</hi> of thoſe <hi>middle</hi> Beings or <hi>Mediatours:</hi> Even as it is a piece of <hi>boldneſs</hi> to preſent a Petition to an <hi>Earthly</hi> Prince, but by the hand of an <hi>Interceſſor,</hi> or ſome <hi>Maſter of Requeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. And ſo, laſtly, it was the Cuſtome of Heathens, to call upon ſome <hi>Demon, Soul,</hi> or <hi>Spirit</hi> to <hi>ſolicite</hi> and <hi>mediate</hi> for them unto the <hi>ſupream God,</hi> and to depend upon <hi>them,</hi> as their <hi>immediate</hi> Patrons, and to expect all their Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions to be anſwered by <hi>their care,</hi> and all good things, both for them and theirs, to be brought unto them by the hands of <hi>theſe Mediators,</hi> to whoſe Cuſtody and Protection they did ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>devote</hi> and <hi>commit</hi> themſelves. This is a ſhort and plain account of the Creed and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of the <hi>Ancient Pagans;</hi> by what we can learn from the moſt ſagacious, dilligent, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitive Writers.</p>
            <p>And by this it will appear what a <hi>correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> and <hi>likeneſs</hi> there is between <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Heatheniſm</hi> in this particular, concerning their <hi>Applications</hi> unto, and their <hi>Dependances</hi> upon certain <hi>Mediators,</hi> whoſe <hi>Intereſt</hi> they conceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to be ſo great in the <hi>Supream</hi> and <hi>Soveraign Numen,</hi> that they <hi>reſted</hi> confidently in <hi>their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion</hi> and power, in all <hi>Caſes, Circumſtances,</hi> and <hi>Conditions</hi> of Life. For (that I may give you ſome particular and known Inſtances:) the Heathens were wont to engage certain <hi>Demons,</hi> or <hi>Spirits</hi> of the other world, to be their <hi>Tute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:52826:20"/>
               <hi>Deities,</hi> to take the Patronage of their <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, Cities,</hi> and <hi>Habitations;</hi> ſuch was <hi>Bel</hi> to the <hi>Babylonians, Oſiris</hi> to the <hi>Aegyptians, Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> to the <hi>Lemnians, Pallas</hi> to the <hi>Trojans, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerva</hi> to the <hi>Athenians, Apollo</hi> to the <hi>Delphicks, Juno</hi> to the <hi>Carthaginians,</hi> and the like. Juſt ſo have the deluded Romaniſts engaged St. <hi>James</hi> to be the <hi>Tutelar Saint</hi> for <hi>Spain, Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> for <hi>Rome, Denis</hi> for <hi>France, Martin</hi> for <hi>Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, Nicolas</hi> for <hi>Moſcovia, Ambroſe</hi> for <hi>Milan, Hulderick</hi> for <hi>Auguſta,</hi> our Lady for I know not how many <hi>Cities</hi> and <hi>Corporations;</hi> and every <hi>particular Child</hi> is taught to chooſe him a <hi>Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> Saint for his <hi>own Perſon,</hi> and to pray dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See the Childs Catechiſme printed at Paris.</hi> 1672.</note> to him in this Form, <hi>Glorious Saint</hi> N. <hi>whom the divine Providence hath allotted for my Pattern on Earth and my Patron in Heaven; obtain (I beſeech you) for me, your poor Pupil, ſo to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate here your Vertues, that I may be made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of your Glory.</hi> Again<hi>:</hi> The Heathens had divers <hi>inferiour Deities</hi> and <hi>Mediators</hi> belonging to their ſeveral <hi>Trades</hi> and <hi>Profeſſions</hi> Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen had their <hi>Ops</hi> and <hi>Sylvanus;</hi> Mariners had their <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux;</hi> Travellers had their <hi>Hercules;</hi> Shepheards had their <hi>Pan;</hi> Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars had their <hi>Apollo;</hi> Souldiers had their <hi>Mars;</hi> and Theeves had their <hi>light-fingured Mercury.</hi> Even ſo have <hi>theſe</hi> ſilly deluded wretches their <hi>peculiar Saints:</hi> Phyſitians have their <hi>Coſmus</hi> and <hi>Damianus;</hi> Painters their Saint <hi>Luke;</hi> Potters have their <hi>Godrus;</hi> Huntſmen their <hi>Euſtacius;</hi> Seamen their Saint <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi> Saint <hi>Clement,</hi> and our Lady; Lawyers have their <hi>Juno;</hi> Smiths
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52826:21"/>
have their <hi>Eulogius,</hi> and Harlots themſelves have their <hi>Saint Magdalen and Saint Afra.</hi> Once more; they have (as the old <hi>Heathens</hi> had) par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular propitions <hi>Spirits,</hi> and <hi>Orators</hi> for <hi>parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Diſeaſes and Griefs;</hi> as <hi>Cornelius</hi> for the <hi>Falling Sickneſs, Barbara</hi> againſt <hi>ſudden Death, Liberius</hi> for <hi>the Stone, Apollonia</hi> for the <hi>Tooth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ach, Otilia</hi> for <hi>Sore eyes, Roche</hi> againſt <hi>the Plague, Petronilla</hi> for <hi>the Fever,</hi> Saint <hi>John</hi> and Saint <hi>Bennet againſt Poyſon,</hi> Saint <hi>Antony</hi> for the <hi>Ery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſipelas, Romanus</hi> for <hi>Demoniacks,</hi> and Saint <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet</hi> for <hi>Women in Travel,</hi> and <hi>Faelicitas</hi> for ſuch as are <hi>Barren.</hi> Laſtly they have particular Saints for the ſafety of <hi>themſelves,</hi> and <hi>their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſorts of Goods:</hi> They have <hi>Antony</hi> for their <hi>Swine, Wendeline</hi> for their <hi>Sheep, Pelagius</hi> for their <hi>Oxen,</hi> Saint <hi>Gall</hi> for their <hi>Geeſe,</hi> Saint <hi>Loy</hi> for their <hi>Horſes, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> for their <hi>Vineyards, Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi> againſt <hi>Fires,</hi> Saint <hi>Michael</hi> and Saint <hi>George</hi> againſt <hi>all their Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Inſtances I have collected, not ſo much out of a deſign to render their Religion <hi>ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous,</hi> as to open the eyes of thoſe ignorant People, who are deluded by <hi>crafty</hi> and <hi>evil Men,</hi> and whom I pity with my Soul. Alas! miſerable were thoſe Creatures in the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> time, who were taught by Hereticks to pray unto <hi>Angels,</hi> to invocate and conſide in <hi>Angels,</hi> as their <hi>Mediators and Patrons</hi> in the Court of Heaven: but (God help them) how miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble are thoſe poor Souls, I now ſpeak of, who are taught to <hi>do this,</hi> and <hi>much more!</hi> Not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to adore and depend on thoſe that are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52826:21"/>
               <hi>Miniſtring Spirits,</hi> but moreover to worſhip and repoſe their truſt (both for their preſent and eternal ſafety) in <hi>little</hi> (and many times very <hi>naughty) Creatures,</hi> whoſe names they are pleaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for their <hi>Intereſt</hi> ſake, and for ſome <hi>ſelf-ends,</hi> to enter into the <hi>Regiſter</hi> and <hi>Catalogue</hi> of Saints! But they have taken their Copy from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion of thoſe, whom Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of in my Text, that had ſtrong deluſions ſent them, that they ſhould believe a Lie, becauſe they lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not the Truth, that they might be ſaved. And <hi>yet</hi> I have <hi>more</hi> to ſay of them <hi>ſtill.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="sermon">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:52826:22"/>
            <head>ANCIENT and MODERN DELUSIONS, Diſcourſed of in three SERMONS Upon 2 THES. 2. 11.</head>
            <head>SERM. III.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2. THES. 2. 11.</bibl>
               <q>And for this cauſe God ſhall ſend them ſtrong Delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, that they ſhould believe a Lye.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>FOR, Fourthly, there is yet <hi>another</hi> thing obſervable of thoſe Deceivers in the dayes of the Apoſtles, that they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to <hi>great Auſterities of Life,</hi> in <hi>mortifying their Fleſh,</hi> and <hi>diſciplining their Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> and abridging themſelves of that <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> which God had <hi>allowed</hi> in the uſe of his Creatures. S. <hi>Paul</hi> takes notice in two ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral places, that <hi>they forbad to marry, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to obſtain from meats,</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 3. and that <hi>they neglected the body by obſerving theſe hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Ordinances, touch not, taſte not, handle not,</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:52826:22"/>
Col. 2. 21. They pretended to be more <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect</hi> and <hi>Holy</hi> than other men, in uſing thoſe ſeverities towards the Body, which others nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did, nor thought themſelves obliged to uſe. Theſe <hi>things have indeed a ſhew of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 23. and 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 2. He gave theſe Deceivers this Character, that they <hi>ſpake Lyes in Hypocriſie;</hi> abuſed the World by pretences of extraordinary <hi>Sanctity</hi> and <hi>Mortification,</hi> becauſe they were ſo ſtrict in theſe <hi>outward</hi> obſervances. And are not the <hi>Modern Severities,</hi> which the Romaniſts lay ſo much ſtreſs upon, ſo many <hi>Apiſh Reſemb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lances</hi> of theſe Ancient Deluſions? Their forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all <hi>Monaſtick</hi> perſons and <hi>Clergy-men</hi> to Marry, as if it were unbecoming the <hi>Sacred<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of their Profeſſion; their commanding certain <hi>Religious Orders,</hi> ſuch as the <hi>Benedictines</hi> and <hi>Carthuſians,</hi> to eat no manner of <hi>Fleſh</hi> all their days; their General Laws touching the <hi>choice</hi> of <hi>meats</hi> at certain times, which are impoſed upon <hi>All</hi> as <hi>Religious</hi> ordinances, and <hi>neceſſary</hi> to be obſerved under pain of <hi>Anathema;</hi> what is all this, but a <hi>reviving</hi> of the Doctrines of the Old Gnoſticks, and a <hi>new Edition</hi> of thoſe Cheats and Impoſtures, which were condemned by the Church in its moſt <hi>Primitive</hi> Ages?</p>
            <p>As near as I can I will do them no wrong in this particular. The Caſe, I confeſs, in ſome reſpects is not altogether the <hi>ſame,</hi> and yet in other reſpects it is not altogether <hi>dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent.</hi> It is not the ſame on this account,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52826:23"/>
becauſe ſome Ancient Deceivers condemned Marriage as one of the <hi>Devils</hi> works, and forbad the uſe of <hi>Wine</hi> and <hi>Fleſh</hi> as a thing evil and unlawful <hi>in it ſelf.</hi> So <hi>Theodoret</hi> tells us of the followers of <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorcerer; and <hi>Irenaeus</hi> tells us of <hi>Saturninus, Marcion</hi> and the <hi>Eucratitae:</hi> And <hi>Epiphanius</hi> relates of the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iren. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 22. <hi>&amp;</hi> 30. <hi>Epiph. Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ.</hi> 30. <hi>&amp;</hi> 42. <hi>&amp;</hi> 66.</note> 
               <hi>Ebionites</hi> and <hi>Manichees</hi> alſo, how they held <hi>Marriage,</hi> and the uſe of <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> to have been inſtituted by the Devil, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was evil <hi>naturally</hi> and <hi>intrinſically.</hi> This the <hi>Papiſts</hi> do deny as <hi>we</hi> do; and they are very <hi>proud</hi> of this Evaſion, and make uſe of it againſt us, when we diſpute againſt their <hi>ſuperſtitions;</hi> even as <hi>Tertullian</hi> did, diſputing againſt the Church in his book, <hi>de Jejunio,</hi> when he was a <hi>Montaniſt.</hi> This is agreed upon on <hi>all hands,</hi> againſt the firſt Hereticks, that <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hierom. adv. Jovinian. l.</hi> 2.</note> 
               <hi>every Creature of God is good, and nothing to be refuſed, if it be received with thanksgiving,</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 4.</p>
            <p>But then it is to be noted, that in the Apoſtles days ſome were guilty, though not of <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,</hi> yet of great <hi>Superſtition</hi> in this particular. For they granted the uſe of Gods Creatures to be lawful <hi>in it ſelf;</hi> but yet they conceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the <hi>forbearance</hi> of their <hi>Liberty</hi> to be a very <hi>meritorious</hi> Act of <hi>Self-denial,</hi> a great piece of of <hi>perfection,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>direct</hi> Act of <hi>worſhip</hi> as was very <hi>acceptable</hi> and <hi>pleaſing</hi> unto God. S. <hi>Paul,</hi> in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 8. ſpeaking of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>bodily exerciſe,</hi> as a thing of <hi>little profit,</hi> doth plainly glance at the <hi>fooleries</hi> of thoſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:52826:23"/>
men, who placed Religion in <hi>bodily</hi> caſtigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations, in abſtaining from <hi>certain meats</hi> and <hi>drinks,</hi> and from <hi>Marriage;</hi> although they did not look upon theſe things as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable</hi> in their own nature; but refrained from them (as divers did) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for <hi>Diſcipline</hi> ſake, ſuppoſing this abſtinence to be an <hi>Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Piety,</hi> and kind of <hi>Mortification</hi> and <hi>Humility,</hi> that would <hi>purchaſe</hi> and <hi>merit</hi> the Divine favour. And, in <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 23. although he calls this neglecting of the body, <hi>will-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> and <hi>humility</hi> (as thoſe ſuperſtitious wretches did) yet he tells us, that theſe are onely the <hi>Commandments</hi> and <hi>Doctrines of men,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>which tended to corrupt practices by the abuſe of them.</hi> Theſe things had indeed in them a <hi>ſhew of Wiſdome,</hi> as being borrowed of ſome <hi>Philoſophers</hi> (for which reaſon he ſaith, beware leaſt any <hi>ſpoil you through Philoſophy and vain deceit,</hi> verſ. 8.) but yet they were onely <hi>ſpecious,</hi> not <hi>real</hi> or <hi>ſubſtantial</hi> ſervices. And are not thoſe <hi>little</hi> things, ſo religiouſly <hi>practiſed,</hi> and ſo wonderfully <hi>applauded</hi> by the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> (ſuch as <hi>wallowing on the ground, a Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitential ſhift, going bare-foot to a Sepulchre or a Shrine, whippings in the Time of Lent, the wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of</hi> S. Francis <hi>his habit,</hi> and <hi>eſpecially</hi> the <hi>choice</hi> of ſome <hi>meats,</hi> as if it were a <hi>mortal ſin</hi> to eat others, and the forbiding of <hi>Prieſts marriage,</hi> becauſe they that <hi>are in the Fleſh can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not pleaſe God</hi> (as Pope <hi>Siricius</hi> inſolently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed) <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Siric. Ep.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> I ſay are not theſe <hi>pettite</hi> and <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions</hi> obſervations impoſed upon the <hi>Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:52826:24"/>
as <hi>neceſſary</hi> and <hi>meritorious</hi> Acts, a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Copy</hi> and <hi>Tranſcript</hi> of Ordinances, that were condemned of <hi>Old?</hi> Though many are ſuch Fops as to receive them for <hi>Catholick</hi> Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and to confide and truſt in them as a <hi>ſure</hi> way to Heaven; yet that the opinion of their <hi>merit</hi> or <hi>neceſſity</hi> is a groſs and pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable Deluſion, may be eaſily evinced by ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving what St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf ſaid <hi>in the beginning</hi> with reference to <hi>theſe</hi> matters. For<hi>:</hi> 1. <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily exerciſe profiteth little,</hi> in compariſon of that Piety which conſiſteth in the <hi>renovation of the heart,</hi> and the <hi>Crucifixion of the Old man.</hi> Chriſtianity is a <hi>grave</hi> and <hi>ſerious</hi> thing requiring the mortifying of our Luſts, and the inward Sanctity of the Spirit: The <hi>Kingdome of God is not meat and drink, but righteouſneſs, and peace, and joy in the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> Rom. 14. 17.</p>
            <p>2. Theſe <hi>frothy</hi> and <hi>inſignificant</hi> Practices are ſo diſtant from the Rules of <hi>ſolid Religion,</hi> that they are indeed the very <hi>ſcum</hi> of <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſm,</hi> the <hi>Elements</hi> and <hi>Rudiments</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 8, 20. For ſo S. <hi>Jerome</hi> tells us, out of <hi>Cheraemon</hi> the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Hierome lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Jovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian.</hi>
               </note> Stoick, touching the Prieſts in <hi>Egypt;</hi> and out of <hi>Eubulus,</hi> touching the Prieſts of <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thras</hi> in <hi>Perſia;</hi> and out of <hi>Philo</hi> and <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus,</hi> touching the <hi>Eſſenes</hi> (which ſome <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Chemnit. Eraſ. pag.</hi> 124. <hi>de Athen.</hi>
               </note> think that S. <hi>Paul</hi> pointeth to eſpecially,) out of <hi>Xenocrates,</hi> touching the <hi>Athenians,</hi> and out of <hi>Euripides</hi> touching the <hi>Cretians,</hi> though they were <hi>Gluttons:</hi> And the like we find related
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:52826:24"/>
of ſeveral <hi>Heathens more</hi> by <hi>other</hi> Authors; that they uſed <hi>bodily</hi> ſeverities, eſpecially before <note place="margin">
                  <hi>See Dr. Ham. in Tit.</hi> 1. 12. <hi>Volateran. l.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi> 4. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throp. Alex. ab Alex. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 2.</note> they made their adreſſes unto their Gods; that they were wont to <hi>change their garments, and lie upon the bare Earth,</hi> and for ſeveral days to <hi>abſtain from conjugal enjoyments, from Wine and Fleſh, and even from Eggs and Milk as coming of Fleſh;</hi> and that when they took their Repaſt, they did it very <hi>moderately,</hi> and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on very <hi>light</hi> diet, contenting themſelves with <hi>bread,</hi> and <hi>hearbs</hi> and <hi>pulſe,</hi> and things of the <hi>like nature;</hi> and all this, ſuppoſing, that by theſe outward caſtigations and ſeverities, they ſhould make the Gods <hi>favourable</hi> and <hi>propitious</hi> unto them.</p>
            <p>3. And yet, S. <hi>Paul</hi> calls all this <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> (or vain oſtentation) 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. A character, which though it was given by the Apoſtle, of the Impoſtors in his Time, thoſe <hi>Spirits of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, thoſe Apoſtates</hi> from the Faith, who had their <hi>Conſciences ſeared with an hot Iron;</hi> yet it may become the generality of Romaniſts at this day. For they make <hi>marriage unlawful</hi> to thoſe, in whom <hi>fornication</hi> is counted <hi>no ſin:</hi> They call it <hi>faſting</hi> when they <hi>forbear Fleſh,</hi> tho they <hi>ſurfeit</hi> with the moſt delicate <hi>Fiſh,</hi> and the moſt generous <hi>Wines:</hi> And ſo they have found out a very <hi>lucky</hi> way to <hi>faſt,</hi> and yet to fare as <hi>ſumptuouſly,</hi> as any Scholar of <hi>Epicurus</hi> or <hi>Apicius</hi> could wiſh to do; to faſt until their girdles crack; to faſt till they are as fat as Boars in a frank; and to mortifie their fleſh till their ſides are, <hi>ſuccidiae Gehennae,</hi> as S. <hi>Jerome</hi> ſpeaks,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:52826:25"/>
like ſo many flitches to be ſmoked in Hell. This is far <hi>ſhort</hi> of the auſterities of thoſe <hi>Pagans</hi> and <hi>Hereticks</hi> of old; for they <hi>faſted</hi> indeed, and fared <hi>hard</hi> too, when their Faſt was <hi>broken,</hi> and had greater Reaſon to plead the Merit of their Works, and to call themſelves ſo many <hi>mortified Saints,</hi> and yet even theſe were Cheats and Deceivers, who abuſed ſilly people, that for their ſins were delivered up to <hi>ſtrong Delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, that they ſhould believe a Lie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>5. Tonching which Impoſtors there is yet a fifth thing obſervable; that <hi>notwithſtanding</hi> their ſpecious and popular pretenſions, they were given to ſuch <hi>licentious</hi> courſes, and <hi>corrupted</hi> the World with ſuch <hi>impious</hi> and <hi>damnable</hi> doctrines as brought a <hi>Reproach</hi> upon Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and made the Church of Chriſt to be <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Juſtin. Mart. Apol.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; Dial. cum Tryp. Min. Fael.</hi>
               </note> and <hi>evil</hi> ſpoken of for their ſakes. All the ancient Writers have obſerved over and over; how addicted they were to <hi>laſciviouſneſs,</hi> and taught men ſuch <hi>abominable</hi> kinds of <hi>uncleanneſs,</hi> as cannot be named without a bluſh. They taught, that in <hi>Times of Perſecution, men might worſhip the Heathen Gods, and eat of ſuch things</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iren. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 23.</note> 
               <hi>as had been offered unto Devils.</hi> They taught, that men might tell any <hi>lies for their ſafety,</hi> and to avoid danger might <hi>equivocate,</hi> and <hi>deny the Faith of Chriſt with their mouths,</hi> ſo <hi>they did not do it in their hearts.</hi> They taught, that it was lawful <hi>to betray and perſecute</hi> thoſe Chriſtians that were <hi>ſincere</hi> and <hi>ſteddy,</hi> and that it was a piece of <hi>good ſervice</hi> unto God, even to <hi>kill</hi> them. They taught, that <hi>Inceſt,</hi> and <hi>Adultery,</hi> and <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:52826:25"/>
were <hi>empty</hi> words, and that the moſt <hi>villainous</hi> ſorts of <hi>Luſt</hi> had nothing of <hi>Sin</hi> or <hi>Impurity</hi> in them. In a word, they did not ſtick at any thing that was <hi>evil,</hi> but were ſuch <hi>Patrons</hi> of all manner of wickedneſs, that in many places of Scripture they are called, <hi>Wolves, Dogs, Blaſphemers, Traitors, Lovers of pleaſures, houſe-creepers,</hi> and <hi>enticers of ſilly women laden with ſins, deſpiſers of government, ſeparatiſts, ſenſualiſts, filthy dreamers, ſcoffers walking after their own luſts, turning the Grace of God into laſciviouſneſs, and denying the Lord that bought them.</hi> Theſe are the plain Characters that were cut out upon the foreheads of that <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly</hi> brood, the followers of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> in the moſt <hi>Primitive</hi> Ages. And now to draw a <hi>Parellel</hi> between <hi>them</hi> and the modern <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> a man might wonder, that they, who <hi>cry</hi> up <hi>Good Works</hi> to the Skyes, ſhould be the Teachers of ſuch things as are quite <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> to Godlineſs, and utterly <hi>deſtructive</hi> of the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Subſtance</hi> of Religion. But here lyes one main peice of <hi>Sophiſtry,</hi> that by <hi>Good Works</hi> they mean, the <hi>hearing of Maſs,</hi> the mumbling over ſome <hi>Ave Maryes</hi> and <hi>Pater Noſters,</hi> abſtinence from <hi>Fleſh</hi> at certain times, and ſuch like Acts of obedience to the Laws of their <hi>Church.</hi> But as for thoſe Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues which are <hi>morally,</hi> and <hi>eternally neceſſary,</hi> as <hi>Love, Humility, Subjection, Charity</hi> and the reſt, they lay ſo little ſtreſs upon them, that they ſuppoſe them to be <hi>diſpenſable,</hi> and of no great moment. For what ſaith the great Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:52826:26"/>
               <hi>Bellarmine.</hi> Why, even this, <hi>that men muſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellarm. de Rom. Pontif. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>acquieſce in the judgement of the Pope; and though he ſhould chance to err in commanding to that which is a vice, or forbidding that which is a Virtue, the Church is bound to believe vices to be good,</hi> and <hi>virtues</hi> to be <hi>evil.</hi> And ſo he ſaith elſewhere, that <hi>Chriſt gave unto</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib. in Bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain, c.</hi> 13.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> (and in him to his Succeſſors) <hi>full power to make that a ſin, which is not ſin, and to make that to be no ſin which indeed is a ſin.</hi> I am very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, there never was a more <hi>deviliſh</hi> Principle taught by the moſt helliſh Impoſtors that liv'd yet in <hi>any Age</hi> of the Church. Yet this is the Principle which the Romaniſts do go up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and take for granted, that let their Popes <hi>teach</hi> what they will, it muſt be <hi>true,</hi> let them <hi>forbid</hi> what they will, it muſt be <hi>evil;</hi> let them <hi>require</hi> what they will, it muſt be <hi>good;</hi> and let them <hi>diſpenſe</hi> with what they will, it muſt be <hi>lawful,</hi> even <hi>in foro interno</hi> in the Court of Conſcience. Now, do but obſerve what are the things, which thoſe <hi>precious Infallible Guides teach?</hi> Why, that men may be ſaved by the <hi>Merits of Saints,</hi> and ſo need not work out their <hi>own Salvation;</hi> that they are juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed before God, if they do but <hi>confeſs</hi> their Sins to a Prieſt, and undergo a ſlight and a cheap Pennance, when the Prieſt hath ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved them; that if they die in the guilt of any <hi>Venial</hi> Sins, they ſhall go no further than <hi>Purgatory,</hi> and ſhall ſoon be ſent thence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Heaven</hi> by a good <hi>Legacy,</hi> by a <hi>few Maſſes,</hi> and by the <hi>Popes</hi> indulgence; and that the Pope hath Authority and Power to Pardon,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:52826:26"/>
               <hi>judicially</hi> the ſins of all men, paſt, preſent and to come, even to the Term of ten thouſand years. Again; what is it which they do <hi>forbid?</hi> Why, to be in Charity with thoſe whom they call Hereticks, to hearken to their Counſels and Arguments, to diſcourſe with them about mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, to look into their Bibles, and to examine the ground of their <hi>own</hi> Faith, and whatſoever elſe tendeth to the prejudice of the Roman Cauſe, is utterly forbidden under the pain of a Curſe. But as the Old Hereticks <hi>forbore</hi> that which they might and ought to have done, but were very <hi>earneſt</hi> for whatſoever was utterly <hi>unlawful;</hi> ſo theſe, while they tye men <hi>up</hi> from things that are <hi>honeſt</hi> and <hi>lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> do not only let them <hi>looſe,</hi> but <hi>drive</hi> them alſo to things, which the Laws of <hi>God</hi> and of <hi>Nature</hi> have ſeverely <hi>interdicted.</hi> They re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire them to reſign up their Senſes, Reaſon and Conſciences into their hands; to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute all that are not of the <hi>ſame Opinions,</hi> though of the <hi>ſame Faith</hi> with them; to <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert</hi> Kingdomes; to <hi>compaſs</hi> Sea and Land to <hi>Poyſon</hi> and <hi>Aſſaſſinate</hi> Princes; and if by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence they be deteſted, to <hi>Lie ſtrenuouſly,</hi> and to <hi>forſwear the Fact,</hi> and to <hi>proteſt</hi> their <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence</hi> with the moſt <hi>bitter Execrations,</hi> even at the <hi>laſt minute,</hi> when their Souls are imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to appear before that <hi>righteous</hi> Judge, who is is the <hi>ſearcher of the heart.</hi> And of the ſame nature are thoſe things which they <hi>allow</hi> and <hi>diſpence</hi> with. Witneſs that <hi>Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> they give men inſtead of <hi>Marrying</hi> to <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate;</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:52826:27"/>
to act the greateſt <hi>Cruelties</hi> that the moſt Savage Wits can invent; to <hi>equivocate</hi> and <hi>diſſemble,</hi> and <hi>deal falſly,</hi> to break Oaths, though never ſo ſtrict and ſacred, and if need require, to <hi>deny their Faith,</hi> and to <hi>take the Sacrament,</hi> even againſt their Conſciences, and for no other end but to <hi>abuſe</hi> and <hi>deceive the World.</hi> Briefly; witneſs thoſe diſpenſations for <hi>Adulteries,</hi> for <hi>Murders,</hi> for <hi>Killing ones Father</hi> or <hi>Mother,</hi> and for many unnatural and moſt horrid impieties: of which we have <note place="margin">Mr. Eganes Rates.</note> ſome account given us by one who was of their own Communion; and a more full ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count may be ſeen in their <hi>Taxa Camera,</hi> a Book publickly printed, of which their own <hi>Eſpenae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cited by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop Taylor, in his Diſſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, part.</hi> 1. <hi>ſect.</hi> 5.</note> ſaith, <q>that it is a Book, in which a Man may learn more wickedneſs, than in all the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maries of Vice publiſhed in the World: and yet to them that will pay for it, there is given <hi>to many</hi> a Licenſe, and <hi>to all</hi> an Abſolution, for the greateſt and moſt horrid <hi>Sins.</hi>
               </q> It is no wonder to me that the Romaniſts generally are ſuch <hi>vile, inhumane,</hi> and <hi>more</hi> than <hi>Barbarous</hi> creatures, having Conſciences ſeared with an hot iron; eſpecially the <hi>Italians,</hi> who live near the <hi>Receipt of Cuſtome,</hi> and under the <hi>Noſe</hi> of that <hi>monſtrous Head</hi> of the Church, who can make <hi>Villany, Nothing.</hi> And I am confident, that no <hi>Leviathans,</hi> whether of <hi>former</hi> or <hi>later</hi> Ages, have bred ſo many <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> as that Church which calls her ſelf <hi>Catholick,</hi> and takes upon her to remove all <hi>boundaries</hi> of good and evil, and either to <hi>command</hi> or to <hi>allow</hi> whatſoever is
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:52826:27"/>
contrary to Eternal Reaſon, repugnant to Gods Word, injurious to all Civil Societies, ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to Mankind, ſcandalous to Religion, and deſtructive of its very <hi>Being</hi> and <hi>Nature.</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly that Character did never better befit any <hi>other</hi> Sect, which Saint <hi>Paul</hi> gave of the <hi>old Gnoſticks,</hi> that they <hi>had the form of Godlineſs, but denied the Power thereof,</hi> 2 Tim. 3. 5.</p>
            <p>6. And yet laſtly, it is obſervable of thoſe old Deceivers, that they pretended <hi>Miracles,</hi> and vied with the Apoſtles themſelves in <hi>work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Wonders,</hi> thinking to make their <hi>Deluſions plauſible</hi> by the ſame <hi>means</hi> and <hi>methods,</hi> which ſerved at firſt for the <hi>confirmation</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> All ancient Eccleſiaſtical Writers have obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the firſt Impoſtors were <hi>Magicians;</hi> and that by inchantments, and the help of the <hi>Devil,</hi> they did many things which paſt for <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles.</hi> We read of <hi>Simon</hi> the firſt <hi>Heretick,</hi> and the <hi>Father</hi> of thoſe Sorcerers, that he did <hi>flie in the air;</hi> that he made <hi>Statues</hi> to <hi>walk,</hi> and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cyril. Cat</hi> 5. <hi>Chryſ. Hom.</hi> 19. <hi>in c.</hi> 7. <hi>Mat.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>move like men;</hi> and that he <hi>would caſt himſelf into the flames, and yet come off without being burnt.</hi> And ſo we find of <hi>Marcus,</hi> that he was wont to make a long Prayer at his conſecrating the Cup, and made the Wine to change its colour, and to look of a deep red; and then he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, <hi>that ſome of Chriſts blood had dropt into</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iren. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>the Chalice.</hi> And many more inſtances might be reckoned up, had I but time to ſearch into An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity. It ſufficeth, what Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly of theſe Apoſtates, that tho they taught <hi>Doctrines of Devils,</hi> yet their <hi>coming was after</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:52826:28"/>
               <hi>the working of Satan, with all power, and ſigns, and lying wonders,</hi> in this 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 9. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> notes; with ſuch wonders, as <hi>either were Impoſtures,</hi> or <hi>tended to confirm an Impoſture.</hi> Had not our Saviour Chriſt foretold, <hi>Matth.</hi> 24. 24. <hi>That falſe Teachers ſhould ariſe, and ſhew ſuch great ſigns and wonders, as would (if it were poſſible) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the very Elect:</hi> Had not <hi>Lodovicus Vives</hi> told us, that in his time, ſome counted it a <hi>piece</hi> of <hi>Piety</hi> to <hi>coin Lies</hi> for Religion: and were not the World fraughted with variety of <hi>Legends,</hi> and thouſands of Stories touching <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles</hi> done at the <hi>Shrines</hi> and by the <hi>Reliques</hi> of Saints; it would be the <hi>greateſt Prodigy</hi> to me, that in theſe dayes, Men ſhould have the confidence to talk of <hi>Miracles,</hi> ſince the Truth of Religion hath been ſo abundantly confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Yet ſuch is the <hi>Folly</hi> and <hi>Impudence</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that they are not aſham'd to fill our ears with ſuch <hi>Comical Stories</hi> (ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of them fabulous, many ridiculous, and all of them impertinent) that were it fit to make this Houſe a Theatre, I would deſire no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Subject, whereby to expoſe their Religion. But my buſineſs is briefly to ſhew, that theſe are ſtrong Deluſions, however ſome credulous and ſilly people do believe them as firmly as the very Creed.</p>
            <p>In order to our proceeding two things muſt be premiſed.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there are two ſorts of Miracles. Some are <hi>properly</hi> ſo called, <hi>real</hi> and <hi>true</hi> Miracles, ſuch
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:52826:28"/>
as cannot be wrought by any ſecond Cauſes, but by the <hi>immediate</hi> hand of God <hi>alone.</hi> Others a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain are improperly ſo called, rather <hi>Prodigies</hi> than <hi>true Miracles,</hi> ſuch as are not effected by any <hi>natural</hi> and <hi>ordinary</hi> cauſes here <hi>among us,</hi> but by ſome <hi>inviſible created Spirits,</hi> who, by Gods permiſſion, produce ſuch ſupernatural ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects, as do ſtrike the vulgar ſort into aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſerve to bring the Inſtruments thereof into admiration: Of this ſort was thoſe wrought of old by the Egyptian Sorcerers, in <hi>Exod.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Miracles are not to be heeded without <hi>Conſideration</hi> had of thoſe <hi>Doctrines,</hi> which they are intended to confirm. For if they ſerve to promote <hi>Idolatry,</hi> or to rob God of <hi>any</hi> of his <hi>Honor</hi> (things plainly condemned by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt in Scripture) they are to be <hi>rejected</hi> without further examination; it being not to be ſuppoſed, that God will contradict <hi>himſelf,</hi> or ſet his Seal to a <hi>Lie;</hi> but rather to be Believed, that he doth only permit An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels or Devils to ſhew ſuch wonders for the <hi>probation</hi> and <hi>tryal</hi> of Mens Faith, or in <hi>ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance</hi> for their Sins. This is clear from <hi>Deut.</hi> 13. 1, 2, 3. <hi>If there ariſe among you a Prophet, and giveth thee a ſign or a wonder, and the ſign or the wonder come to paſs, whereof he ſpake unto thee, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing let us go after other Gods, and ſerve them; thou ſhalt not hearken unto the words of that Prophet,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Theſe things being taken for granted we affirm,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That the ſigns and wonders, which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> boaſteth of, are <hi>not</hi> in any wiſe <hi>true Miracles,</hi> done by the <hi>power</hi> of God, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:52826:29"/>
Chriſt and his Apoſtles were indued; but that they are either ſo many <hi>Lies</hi> and <hi>Forgeries,</hi> or ſo many <hi>Diabolical operations</hi> at the beſt. For what do they pretend to do, but in a <hi>corner</hi> and among <hi>themſelves?</hi> Whereas true Miracles were acted before the Sun, and before the eyes of thoſe who were <hi>Enemies</hi> to truth; becauſe a true Miracle is alwayes for <hi>conviction,</hi> and ſo muſt be <hi>publick.</hi> And if theſe men are armed with omnipotence, why do they not ſhew <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> the finger of God, who are ready to <hi>reſiſt</hi> their <hi>Doctrines</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> even unto Blood? and beſides it is to be conſidered, that how great <hi>ſoever</hi> their pretended Miracles are, we will ſhew them <hi>as great,</hi> which have been done by unbelievers, not only by the <hi>Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> but alſo by <hi>Apollonius Tyaneus,</hi> by <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> and other <hi>Roman Emperors,</hi> and by <hi>Accius Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius,</hi> a Pagan, of whom <hi>Apuleius,</hi> tells us, that <note place="margin">Miraculum cotis. Apul.</note> 
               <hi>he divided a Stone with a Razor.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If theſe <hi>Miracles</hi> were <hi>more</hi> for <hi>number,</hi> and <hi>greater</hi> for the <hi>nature</hi> of them than they are, yet are they to be exploded and hiſſed at by all Lovers of the Truth, becauſe they <hi>tend,</hi> not to the confirmation of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Faith, but to <hi>different</hi> ends clearly. It is obſervable, that when the Roman Doctors would prove the verity of the Articles of our <hi>Common Creed,</hi> they talk not of <hi>Miracles,</hi> but have recourſe unto the <hi>Scriptures.</hi> But ſeeing they can find nothing <hi>there,</hi> which counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanceth the <hi>worſhipping of Relicks and Images</hi> and the like, they appeal always to <hi>ſtrange</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:52826:29"/>
and <hi>mighty works,</hi> pretended to have been done by ſuch and ſuch a <hi>Saint,</hi> to give war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to their Superſtitions and Idolatry. Now theſe things are repugnant to the Word of God, and to the Doctrine of God our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our; and therefore it is preſumable, that they are <hi>Impoſtures</hi> and <hi>Cheats</hi> put upon men by the <hi>Father of Lies,</hi> thereby to advance the Intereſt of his Kingdome. For all theſe Miracles, ſo highly cryed up, ſerve to no good purpoſes, but to ſome <hi>pitiful,</hi> or <hi>ſinful</hi> ends; either to bring their <hi>Monaſteries</hi> and <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> into veneration, or to encourage the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations of Saints,</hi> or to bring <hi>honour to the Maſs,</hi> or to promote the <hi>adoration of the Hoſt,</hi> or the <hi>Croſs,</hi> or the like <hi>monſtrous Innovati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> So they tell us, that <hi>St.</hi> Antony <hi>was heard at two miles diſtance, while he was preaching;—</hi>That <hi>St.</hi> Denis <hi>took up his own head, after 'twas cut off, and carried it in his arms;—</hi>That <hi>St.</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minick <hi>was wont to plague the Devil, pulling off his Feathers when he appeared to him in the ſhape of a Sparrow, and burning his toes when he trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled him in the form of a Monkey;—</hi>That St. <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis was transformed into the form of our Saviour, with his five Wounds imprinted upon him;—</hi>That St. <hi>Ignatius's picture quenched a fire in a Barn that was all on a flame, and cured a Spaniard of</hi> Mendoza <hi>of the black Ague;—</hi>That St. <hi>Xavier having dropt his Crucifix into the Sea to allay a Tempeſt, recovered it again by the miniſtery of a Crab-Fiſh, that carried it many leagues, and brought it a ſhore with a great deal of reverence;—</hi>That
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:52826:30"/>
Saint <hi>Patrick, while he was yet in his Mothers bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, heard the Iriſh Infants crying to him to come and ſet them free;—</hi>That Saint <hi>Nicholas faſted eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry wedneſday and friday, whilſt he was a ſucking Child;—</hi>That <hi>Bartolomy of</hi> Durham <hi>confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded an Evil Angel, by throwing at him a pot of Holy Water;—</hi>That Saint <hi>Moedoc rode over a Lake in a Chariot, and left upon the waters the print of the wheels;—</hi>That a <hi>Mule was made to leave his Provender to adore the Sacrament;—</hi>That a <hi>Sheep was ſo devout, as to attend the Maſs, and to bleat before the Altar of the bleſſed Virgin, and did humble obeiſance at the elevation of the Hoſt;—</hi>That <hi>by the ſign of the Croſs a Birds head was ſet on, that had been pulled off by the Boys, and great flakes of Ice were turned into billets, and a ſucking Child was made to ſpeak,</hi> and <hi>thouſands</hi> have been healed of all manner of Diſeaſes;—That <hi>Devils have been brought to confeſſion by the virtue of the Ladies Pſalter and the Roſary;</hi> and that <hi>Evil Spirits have ſneaked out of perſons poſſeſſed by the Repeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a few Ave Maryes; and</hi> that at Saint <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vais his Monaſtry in</hi> Paris, <hi>a hive of Bees were ſo Religious, as to build a Chappel of Wax in honor of the holy Wafer, that was put in among them; and framed a Table, a Pix, and even Bells, all of Wax; and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved the Canonical hours, and turned their hive into a Religious Houſe:</hi> Only there was wanting a Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtry of Drones. This is but a ſhort account of their great Miracles, a larger Collection where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I have by me, and they ſhall have it too, when they require it, and there ſhall be occaſion for it.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:52826:30"/>
In the mean while it ſufficeth to ſee what <hi>tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling</hi> Miracles theſe are, which they pretend to; and that they come ſo far <hi>ſhort</hi> of thoſe ſigns and wonders, which the more <hi>cunning Gnoſticks</hi> did work of old, that the <hi>only great Miracle</hi> is, that people ſhould be ſo void of <hi>ſenſe,</hi> and <hi>common Reaſon,</hi> as to give credit to them. But yet I conſider, that <hi>this is no very great Miracle</hi> neither, becauſe many have <hi>been and are delivered up to ſtrong deluſions to believe a lie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From all that hath been ſpoken upon this ſubject, we may ſee in ſhort, what <hi>little</hi> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon theſe fine Chriſtians have to call themſelves <hi>Catholicks,</hi> and the <hi>only Catholicks</hi> in the World; and for a what <hi>ſtrange</hi> and <hi>ſottiſh</hi> Religion it is, that <hi>Cities</hi> muſt be <hi>fired,</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered,</hi> and <hi>Princes deſtroyed,</hi> and <hi>Kingdomes divided,</hi> and the World turned upſide down. Whereas he is a <hi>true Catholick,</hi> that holdeth the <hi>Catholick doctrine, the Faith that once was delivered unto the Saints,</hi> the Sum whereof is compriſed in the Apoſtles <hi>Creed,</hi> which is indeed the <hi>true Catholick</hi> Faith; theſe great preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders have added <hi>new Articles</hi> unto the <hi>Old</hi> number, and ſo have ſpoyled the <hi>Ancient</hi> pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of Religion by ugly additions; and yet will be ſo inſolent as to call theſe <hi>corruptions</hi> by the name of <hi>Catholick verities;</hi> although it be made to appear, that they have ranſaked the graves of <hi>Old Hereticks,</hi> and even <hi>raked Hell</hi> it ſelf, to patch up that goodly model, which they would obtrude upon the World.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:52826:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Of the <hi>Simonians</hi> they have learned to <hi>pretend Infallibility,</hi> to <hi>worſhip Images,</hi> to <hi>worſhip An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> to <hi>call</hi> upon <hi>Mediators,</hi> to <hi>prohibite Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage,</hi> to <hi>enjoyn the choice of meats,</hi> to <hi>debauch the World;</hi> and as a colour for all their Intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Uſurpations, to <hi>pretend Miracles.</hi> To which I might add further, that they have learned of the <hi>Marcaeta</hi> to call <hi>Wine Blood;</hi> of the <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taniſts,</hi> to make <hi>Laws</hi> of faſting; of the <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rachitae,</hi> to make works <hi>truely menitorious;</hi> of the <hi>Priſcillianiſts,</hi> to make <hi>Apocryphal</hi> books <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual</hi> with the Word of God: of the <hi>Pelagians,</hi> to Preach up a <hi>poſſibility</hi> of <hi>abſolute Perfection;</hi> of the <hi>Collyridians</hi> to <hi>offer</hi> up <hi>Cakes</hi> to the <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Mary;</hi> of the <hi>Armenians,</hi> to <hi>worſhip</hi> the <hi>Croſs;</hi> of <hi>Petrus Gnaphaeus</hi> to make Prayers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Saints; and of the <hi>Gnoſimachi,</hi> to applaud <hi>Ignorance,</hi> as the <hi>Mother of Devotion.</hi> They are apt Scholars to learn <hi>any thing</hi> but what is good: and they have followed very <hi>fine Guides,</hi> the <hi>very worſt</hi> of Chriſtians (if I may ſo call them) and ſuch as the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church hath marked and condemned for <hi>Hereticks.</hi> And now let God be judge between us and them, where the Deluſions lie, whether <hi>on our</hi> ſide or <hi>on theirs:</hi> And ſo I end.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:52826:31"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A Catalogue of ſome Books printed for and ſold by</hi> Jonathan Edwin <hi>at the</hi> Three Roſes <hi>in</hi> Ludgate-ſtreet.</head>
            <p>A Sermon preached on the Thirtieth of <hi>Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary</hi> 1673/9, being the Anniverſary of the Martyrdome of King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, of bleſſed Memory, and publiſhed at the requeſt of ſome Friends, by <hi>Edward Pelling,</hi> Rector of Saint <hi>Martins Ludgate:</hi> in quarto,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The true Liberty and Dominion of Conſcience</hi> vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated from the Uſurpations and Abuſes of Opinion and Perſwaſion: in octavo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Countermine;</hi> or a ſhort, but true diſcovery of the dangerous Principles and ſecret Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of the Diſſenting Party, eſpecially the Presbyterians, ſhewing, that Religion is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, but Rebellion is intended, and in order thereto, the Foundation of Monarchy in the State, and Epiſcopacy in the Church are undermined: in octavo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Common Intereſt of King and People,</hi> ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Original, Antiquity, and Excellency of Monarchy compared with Ariſtocracy and Democracy, and perticularly of our Engliſh Monarchy, and that abſolute Papal and Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian popular Supremacy, are utterly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiſtent with Prerogative, Property; and Liberty: in octavo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Project of Peace;</hi> or Unity of Faith and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, the onely expedient to procure
<pb facs="tcp:52826:32"/>
Peace both Forreign and Domeſtique; and to preſerve theſe Nations from the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of Popery, and Arbitrary Tyranny: in octavo.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Cauſes and Remedies of the Diſtempers of the Times,</hi> in certain Diſcourſes of Obedience and Diſobedience: in octavo.</p>
            <p>Two Sermons preached at the Funerals of the Right Honourable <hi>Robert</hi> Lord <hi>Lexington,</hi> and the Lady <hi>Mary</hi> his Wife; by <hi>Samuel Holden,</hi> A. M. late of <hi>Lincoln</hi> Colledge, in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and Chaplain to his Lordſhip, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed: in quarto.</p>
            <p>A Sermon preached <hi>July</hi> 17. 1676. in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral Church of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> in <hi>York,</hi> before the Right honourable Sir, <hi>Francis North,</hi> Lord Chief Juſtice of the Common Pleas; and the honourable, <hi>Vere Bertie</hi> Eſquire, one of the Barons of the Exchequer; his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Judges of Aſſize for the Northern Circuit. by <hi>Thomas Cartwright</hi> D. D. and Dean of <hi>Ripon,</hi> Chaplain in ordinary to his Majeſty.</p>
            <p>A Sermon preached before the King at Whit-Hall, <hi>January</hi> the 9th 1675/6. by <hi>Thomas Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright,</hi> D. D. Chaplain in ordinary to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
